<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Numb[er]. 1. An abstract of some special forreigne occurrences, brought down to the weekly newes, of the 20 of December. Or, The severall passages and novels which have happened in Germany, France, Spaine, Italy, and other places some few moneths since</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1638</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 124 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 48 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A08143</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 18507.277</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S115595</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99850813</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99850813</idno>
            <idno type="VID">16041</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A08143)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 16041)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 905:05)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Numb[er]. 1. An abstract of some special forreigne occurrences, brought down to the weekly newes, of the 20 of December. Or, The severall passages and novels which have happened in Germany, France, Spaine, Italy, and other places some few moneths since</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>96 p. : ill.  </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>printed [by T. Harper?] for Nathaniel Butter and Nicholas Bourne,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>By permission, 1638.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Printer's name conjectured by STC.</note>
                  <note>Formerly STC 82.</note>
                  <note>Now = Newsbooks 277.</note>
                  <note>Identified as STC 82 on UMI microfilm "Early English books, 1475-1640".</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in: Bodleian Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Thirty Years' War, 1618-1648 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Volcanic eruptions --  Azores --  São Miguel Island --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Germany --  History --  1618-1648 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2013-07</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-08</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-09</date>
            <label>Anne Simpson</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-09</date>
            <label>Anne Simpson</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:16041:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Numb.</hi> 1. AN ABSTRACT OF SOME SPECIALL Forreigne Occurrences, brought down to the weekly Newes, of the 20 of December.</p>
            <p>OR,</p>
            <p>The ſeverall paſſages and novels which have happened in <hi>Germany, France, Spaine, Italy,</hi> and other places ſome few moneths ſince.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed for <hi>Nathaniel Butter</hi> and <hi>Nicholas Bourne,</hi> By permiſſion, 1638.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:16041:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:16041:2"/>
            <head>The Currantiers to the Readers.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">G</seg>Entle Readers, this Intelligen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cer the <hi>Curranto</hi> having been long ſilenced, and now permit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted by Authority to ſpeake a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain, preſents you here at firſt with ſuch things as paſſed ſome months ſince, not becauſe we conceive that they are abſolutely No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vels unto you, but firſt becauſe there is fraud in generalities, we thought fit to acquaint you with each particular; and ſecondly, that by theſe Ante<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cedents you may the better underſtand the Conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quents, which wee ſhall now publiſh weekely as heretofore.</p>
            <div type="part">
               <pb facs="tcp:16041:3"/>
               <head>Amongſt other ſpeciall Aviſoes, theſe:</head>
               <p>THe famous battell betwixt D. <hi>Bernard Weymar,</hi> and Generall <hi>Gotz</hi> at the black Wood in <hi>Iuly</hi> laſt paſt.</p>
               <p>The battell of the Prince <hi>Palatine,</hi> and Gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall <hi>Hartzfield</hi> in Weſtphalia neere Minden, where Prince <hi>Robert,</hi> and the Lord <hi>Craven</hi> were taken priſoners.</p>
            </div>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="5" facs="tcp:16041:3"/>
            <head>A PRODIGIOVS Eruption of Fire, which exhaled in the middeſt of the Ocean ſea, over againſt the Iſle of Saint <hi>Michael,</hi> one of the <hi>Tercera's,</hi> and the new Iſland which it hath made. It tooke beginning the third of Iuly of this pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent yeare 1638.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">B</seg>Etwixt the Tercera's Iſlands, ſo known to thoſe who ſaile to the Eaſt and Weſt Indies and to Braſile, there is a ſite of water in the midſt of the ſea, diſtant two leagues from the Iſland of Saint <hi>Michael,</hi> which the adjoining in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>habitants call Ferraria, ſo abounding with fiſh, that it is doubtfull whether there bee any place more plentifull in all the ſeas. In this place nature hath wrought the moſt portentous caſe that the ages have ſeen, it was thus; On the third of the laſt Iuly,
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:16041:4"/> within the bottome of the ſea, which in the ſayd place is one hundred and fifty fadomes deepe, like the ſpringing of a mine, with a horrible noyſe and great horror, a ſpace of earth ſeparated it ſelf, which would take the ſowing of halfe a buſhell of wheate, with the vehemencie and force of an impetuous fire, againſt which all the waters of the ocean ſea it ſelfe could make no reſiſtance, caſting up to the clouds the water and earth in ſevered parts, as it were burning torches, and very great ſtones, ſome whereof aſcending while others deſcended, and ſo encountring each other, returned by vertue of the new impulſe to fly up more than three pikes high: others diſſolved in pieces, did fly as if they had ſai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led large diſtances, and the broken pieces beeing handled, diſſolved into blacke aſhes, and all that cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuit of water changing its nature, like withered and dry wood, miniſtreth matter if not aliment to the fire, which without ceaſing doth continue burning. A fatall wonder, which is ſo much the more, to ſee that with the multitude of ſtones which the fire hath caſt up, there is compoſed and formed a new Iſland, which takes up a league and a half in length, and is threeſcore fadomes high, and it did continue its augmentation and burning until the tenth day of the ſayd Iuly, as appeareth by an aſſured relation which was ſent to his Majeſty, whom God protect, and is in the regiſtry of State belonging to Portu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gall. All the fiſh which were within more than eight leagues diſtance round about, died conſumed,
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:16041:4"/> and made worth nothing; and the ſea caſt forth up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the ſhores of the Iſland of Saint <hi>Michael</hi> ſo great a quantity, that it would have filled many of thoſe ſhips which ſaile to the Eaſt Indies: and leſt the aire ſhould bee infected, they made great pits in which they buried them. All the ſea boyled for many leagues, the ſmell of the brimſtone was felt by the moſt remote of thoſe Iſlands: the ſmoake and the aſhes filled the aire, and hid the light of the Sunne, to the admiration of all the inhabitants of thoſe Iſlands.</p>
            <p>Before this fire there preceded an earthquake, which continued more than eight dayes, perceived in all thoſe ſeas and Iſlands, and with a greater noiſe in that of Saint <hi>Michael;</hi> ſo that the inhabitants ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rified, confounded and aſtoniſhed, leſt they ſhould periſh amidſt the ruines of the buildings, fled into the fields, where they remained for ſome days, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſing, faſting, and making proceſſions of bloud, and other acts of penance as thoſe who feared to to die, either drowned with the Iſlands themſelves, or conſumed and burned with another equall fire.</p>
            <p>Our Lord God was pleaſed that the wind ſhould be from the land, for had it beene from ſea, it had burned all the townes of the neighbouring Iſlands, and would have occaſioned another cineration like that which hapned in thoſe parts in the year 1630.</p>
            <p>There went many perſons to ſound the depth of that place, and they have found that it hath of depth in the ſea more than one hundred and fifty fadoms.
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:16041:5"/> Let the Speculative ponder, and the philoſopher ſearch out the cauſe of ſo portentuous an eff<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ct, in as much as the Mathematician ſeekes rects for his judgement, and the Hiſtorian knowledges for his diſcourſe.</p>
            <closer>
               <dateline>Madrid <date>the eighth of September, 1638.</date>
               </dateline>
            </closer>
            <postscript>
               <p>With Licence in Madrid.</p>
               <closer>
                  <dateline>In the <hi>Imprimierie</hi> of <hi>Franciſco Martinez,</hi> 
                     <date> in the year 1638.</date>
                  </dateline>
               </closer>
            </postscript>
         </div>
         <div type="illustration">
            <pb n="9" facs="tcp:16041:5"/>
            <p>
               <figure>
                  <figDesc>engraving of island created by the volcanic eruption of Sete Cidades off the coast of San Miguel</figDesc>
                  <p>AA. <hi>The places where the fire burſt out.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>BB. <hi>The length of the Iſland.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>C. <hi>The Iſland.</hi>
                  </p>
               </figure>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:16041:6"/>
            <pb n="11" facs="tcp:16041:6"/>
            <head>From <hi>Baſill.</hi> A TRVE AND PARTICVLAR RELA<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, of the famous and bloudy bat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taile, fought the 30 day of Iuly old ſtile, in this preſent yeare 1638. neare the Village of <hi>Wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten-weyer</hi> in the County of <hi>Briſgaw</hi> on the River of Rhyne, how it was firſt begunne, and how it ended according to Gods good will and pleaſure.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>Fter that Duke <hi>Bernhard</hi> of Saxo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Weymar had kept his ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neral Randevouze the 27 of Iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, or 6 of Aug. at <hi>Langendenta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lingen</hi> not farre from <hi>Fry-burg</hi> in the Countie of Briſgaw, and the next day therupo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> following directed his march towards <hi>Kentzingen,</hi> and pitched his Campe neare the ſaid City. His Highnes recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved intelligence by the parties, which he had ſent abroad, that the Imperiall and Bavarian Armies with a great number of Wagons, laden with corne,
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:16041:7"/> meale, and other victuals, were arrived neare the Cloiſter of Shutteren, his Highnes broke up again the ſame evening with his whole Army, &amp; marched the whole night, till unto the dawning of the day to meet them, and on Sunday morning being the 29 of Iuly or 8 of Aug: lighted upon both the Gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall Field-marſhals, the Duke of Savelly, and <hi>Iohn</hi> Count of Goetz with all their forces not far from the aforeſaid Cloyſter of Shutteren neare the Vil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lage of Frieſenheim, aſſaulted immediately their Sentinels conſiſting of commanded Horſemen, tooke priſoners a Lieutenant with eight horſemen, &amp; ſlew ſome more of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, and the reſt he purſued to the maine Imperiall Army and by the helpe of cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain comma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ded troops of foot, co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſiſting for the moſt part of French, took two paſſages, which the Impe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rialliſts had ſtrongly guarded, and ſlew there about 60 of the Imperial ſouldiers; wherefore the Impe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rialiſts to hinder and to prevent a farther purſuite, thought it convenient &amp; good to fire the aforeſaid Village in ſeverall places; both the Field-marſhals being certified of the unexpected comming of his Highneſſe, Duke <hi>Bernhard</hi> of Saxon Weymar and his ſuddaine aſſault, did beginne to march in good order with their whole Army and Artillery, upon an high and very advantageous hill hard by it, and to play from thence with their Canons upon his Highneſſe Forces very fiercely and without cea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing, yet being their Canons plaid too high with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out any great effect and harme; And that they were
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:16041:7"/> anſwered by his Highneſſe Canons divers times, although not ſo fiercely and ſo often, yet with more effect; in the meane time the Muſquetiers skirmiſhed one againſt another, inſomuc<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> that the ſame forenoone, on the Imperiall and B<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>varian ſide, as they themſelves confeſs'd above 120. men were ſlaine; but on his Highneſſe ſide not ab<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>v<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 20. killed, and about 30 wounded. And although the French troopes, that were there, ſeeing they had ſo good ſucceſſe in the beginning, were very eager to climbe up the Hill, and to aſſault the maine Imperi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all Campe, yet his Highneſſe had diſcry'd already, that without great danger and loſſe, nothing could be effected: and therefore found it more conveni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent in his judgement to betake himſelfe into the open field hardby, &amp; to put his men into a right Bat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taile-array, hoping that the aboveſaid Generall Field-marſhals, would likewiſe reſolve to come downe upon his Highneſſe; being prompted to it by a report and generall rumour of long continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance that Field-marſhall <hi>Goetz</hi> deſired much to meet the Duke <hi>Bernhard</hi> upon ſuch tearmes.</p>
            <p>His Ex. wiſhed nothing elſe but the like occaſion: But being both generalls were loth to breake forth out of their advantages in which they lay, and deſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red not to medle further with his Highnes beſides that which had paſſed with the Cannons and ſmall skirmiſhes aforementioned, his Highneſſe about noone retired ſomewhat towards Mohlburg, and thereby gave the more occaſion to both generalls
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:16041:8"/> Feild Marſhalls to betake themſelves likewiſe downe from the advantageous hill, upon which they lay. The night following was ſpent on both ſides with alarum, and the next munday following being the 30 of Iuly, the 9 of Auguſt: his Highneſſe cauſed the ſervice of God and the ſermon of the weeping of Chriſt over Ieruſalem (which the day before by reaſon of thoſe skirmiſhes was neglected) orderly to be performed: and whereas in the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluſion of the ſame ſermon ſtrong proofe was pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duced, how that God Almighty who is a God of long ſufferance doth forbeare a long time the deſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſers and perſecutors of his holy word, and that al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though they be terrible and mighty for a time, yet cauſeth them at laſt to bee confounded and over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>throwne: his Highneſſe hereupon tooke finall re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolution, and immediatly thereupon ſpoke theſe words to all the Cavalliers that were preſent, that without further delay he was reſolved to fall upon the enemie, with a certaine aſſurance, that God Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mighty would grant them this day a glorious victorie, and immediatly thereupon gave order for the whole Armie to breake up, and aſſoone as his Highneſſe had din'd, immediatly tooke horſe, his Highneſſe having received certaine intelligence, that both the general Feild-mariſhalls with all their forces, &amp; proviſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> were already marching upwards towards the river of Rhine, and therefore his High<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, leaſt they ſhould paſſe by and attaine to their end (the victualling of the City and Fort of Bryſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſack)
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:16041:8"/> made the more haſte to prevent them; and thereupon preſently after 12 of the clock at noone near the Village of Wittenweyer (where his High<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe the laſt yeare had his ſconce and Shipbridge) lighted upon the aforeſaid Generalls, yet the ſaid Generalls, having intelligence before of his comm<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, had made themſelves ready in all things and therefore gotten the advantage of the ground to put their Army in battaile-aray, whereas on the other ſide it fell heavie and trobleſome to his High<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe to march through a great wood and over a ſmall Iland, moates and bridges, which were over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grown with thick hedges, which by the help of cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine 100 men of the Imperiall forces if not totally ſtopt, yet for a certaine time might much have hin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred him, but being his Highneſſe found there no oppoſition, hee put his Artillery and the troopes, which he had got over there, at the end of the a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>foreſaid wood into Battaglia, and kept them cloſe together, till he had brought over all his forces and could give in a right order a full aſſault: whereupon the ſhooting with the Cannons was begun on both ſides and continued with great eagerneſſe, inſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>much that his Highneſſe right wing (which was lead by Generall Major <hi>Tupadell</hi>) becauſe the Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>periall and Bavarian right wing was ſelected and conſiſted of the choiceſt of their forces, as namely of the curraſſiers and others of the beſt Regiments, was beaten back a great way, and forced to retire as farre as the reſerve, which was commanded by
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:16041:9"/> Colonell <hi>Canofsky;</hi> and being the ſame ſtood yet ſomewhat farre behind, the Imperialiſts on their ſide ſtood in hope that they had got already a great victory, but that joy laſted not long, becauſe as ſoone as the aforeſaid Generall Major <hi>Tupadell</hi> had come within reach of the ſaid Colonell <hi>Canofsky,</hi> they fell on againe withall poſſible ſpeed upon the aforeſaid left wing, and put the ſame ſo hard to it, that it did as Generall M<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>jor <hi>Tupadell</hi> afore was forced to do, to looke for a ſecond.</p>
            <p>In the meane time Colonell <hi>Roſal</hi> who toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther with the Count of N<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſſaw and the Baron of Pulbus lead Duke <hi>Bernhards</hi> left wing, chaſed the Savelliſh and Goetziſh right wing without any great reſiſtance pell mell into their owne foote forces, and purſued ſo farre after them, that the Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>periall party had great loſſe, and immediatly there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon a part of their foote Forces beganne to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>take themſelves to flight: In the meane time the reſt of the Brigades came very nigh one upon ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and yet the Imperiall Muſquetiers would not give fire, till Duke <hi>Bernhard</hi> of Weymar had drawne certaine ſmall troopes out of his Army, and ſent them cloſe up to the Imperiall Muſqueti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers and cauſed bullets to be changed one with ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, whereupon the maine body of the Army came one upon another, and now this party and then th'other party was aſſaulted by the horſe men, and then ſeconded againe, in which mixture it came ſo farre, that at laſt they did beat the Muſquets one
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:16041:9"/> about another heads, and the Goetziſh attained of Duke <hi>Bernhards</hi> Artilery 3. peeces ſhooting a bul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led of 12. pound, and foure ſmall field peeces: On the other ſide Duke <hi>Bernhard</hi> of Weymar got into his power all the Imperiall and Bavarian Canons, together with all the Bullets and appurtenances, whereupon both ſides made uſe of his enemies Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nons, as much as they would, yet with this remark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able inequallty, that the <hi>Goetziſh</hi> being they were not provided with fitting bullets for thoſe 7 peeces of Ordnance which they had obtained, had but ſmall advantage by them, but the Weymariſh con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinually and with a remarkable effect could ſhoote: Now being it laſted ſo long, ſo that thoſe that be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>longed to the Artillery were quite tired, a part of Duke <hi>Bernhards</hi> horſemen alighted, and ſupplyed the office of the tired Conſtables or Gunners and carryed away the praiſe, that they have ſhot extra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ordinary well: Yet notwithſtanding being the Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perialliſts had ſtill freſh ſupply of more Forces, which conſiſted of old beaten and expert Souldi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers, and found in the Weymariſh the like, they fought ſo ſtoutly on both ſides that not one Squ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, except it was drawn off by force, did leave the field, but did fight ſo valiantly one with another, that each ſide for the ſecond time got his enemies ground, in ſomuch that the victory was doubtfull for five houres together, at laſt they fought onely by way of Squadrons and Regiments one againſt another, whereof each of them would not leave
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:16041:10"/> the field, till it was beaten out of it by maine force, till at laſt the Goetziſh and Savelliſh betooke them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves to flight by whole troops, and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ell one upon anothers baggage, and begun themſelves to pillage their owne; but the Weymariſh followed them cloſe, and chaſed them away from it, and parted the good booty amongſt themſelves, and by that meanes divi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded and ſeperated themſelves ſo farre one from ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, that Duke <hi>Bernhard</hi> of Weymar could no more relye upon his horſemen, but onely with the foot for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, and ſome few troopes of horſe maintained the place of fight, and in that place his Highneſſe was well and thankfully contented with this and other vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctories, which it had pleaſed God Almighty to grant unto him.</p>
            <p>Now when it was come ſo farre, that many of the Commanders wiſhed much joy to his Highneſſe of that glorious victory, Generall Major <hi>Tupadell</hi> was urged by his zeale and eagerneſſe to purſue with ſome ſmall troops of his men after the fugitives; and when he had ſent his troops up and downe, here and there, and thought to returne backe againe with ſome few men thinking that no more of the Imperiall and Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>varian troops were at hand: he was met unawares by an Imperiall troop, which had drawn together a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine, and thus was carried away priſoner: and neere the very place of fight, five Imperiall ſquadrons of horſe, and foure of foot, lay yet on a certaine hill, and a very advantagious place, which made ſhew, as if they would defend themſelves further; but as ſoone
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:16041:10"/> as the maine body of the Wey-mariſh Army came neere unto them, and a blinde alarum was made, they retired immediatly in a great diſorder, and fled to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards Offenburg, where his Excellence Field-mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhall <hi>Goetz</hi> himſelfe ſtayed not above halfe an houre, but with ſixe wagons loaden with baggage, which of all the reſt he had left behinde him there, retired yet the ſame night, together with General Major <hi>Sknetter,</hi> Colonell <hi>Geyling, Truekmuller,</hi> and <hi>Reynach</hi> towards <hi>Overkerk,</hi> into the narrow valley, where his Excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lency cauſed divers high Officers which were carried away from the place of fight either dead, or dyed by the way, to be buried: In the meane time the wayes and paſſages over the high mountaines, (called the <hi>Kniebis</hi>) which were ſtopped by cutting downe of trees, he cauſed by the Country people to be opened, and the reſt of his and the Duke of <hi>Savellies</hi> troopes, as namely 1400 horſe. and 900 foot, yet all in a great confuſion, to march through the ſaid paſſages into the Country of Wirtenberg, and immediately thereupon cauſed the ſaid wayes and paſſages to be digged up a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine, and to be ſtopped with cutting downe of trees, more then they were afore-time. On the other ſide, his Highneſſe Duke <hi>Bernhard</hi> of Weymar took his lodging upon the place of fight amongſt the dead and wounded, where the enemy in the beginning ſtood in battell aray, and there reſted with joy of his extraor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinary great labour, which he had that day, becauſe he himſelfe in perſon hath brought up and lead on almoſt all the Squadrons and Brigads, and many
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:16041:11"/> times he was in the midſt of the enemies troops, and was knowne by many of the Imperiall Officers, which called him by his name, and craved quarter of him: but God Almighty hath protected his Highneſſe ſo farre, that he had not the leaſt hurt, onely upon his armour he had got two ſlaſhes. His Highneſſe motto in this hot and bloudy battell was, <hi>Gott mitt vus:</hi> or in Engliſh, <hi>God with us:</hi> and amongſt the French and other nations then preſent in the battell, which could not well pronounce the German language, their mot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to was <hi>Emanuel.</hi> But amongſt the Goetziſh and Savel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh, they called <hi>Ferdinandus:</hi> the victory conſiſted in theſe points. 1 That his Highneſſe Duke <hi>Bernard</hi> of Saxon Weymar recovered againe not onely all his Canons, which the Imperialiſts during the battell had taken from him, but alſo taken from them all theirs, as many as they had about them; namely, two Demi-Cannons, two great heavy pieces, which they call Boehlers, wherof each did ſhoot 125 l. bullet, three Faulcons, two Falconets, and foure Field-pieces, to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether with all their appurtenances, Bullets, Grana<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>does, Gunne-powder and Matches, which conſiſted of a great quantity; as alſo many wagons loaden with all manner of materials two Field-Smiths, and all ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſaries belonging to the ſtate of a well ordered Artil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lery, together with all the Officers and men belong<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing thereunto. 2 That his Highneſſe hath obtained all the victuals and proviſion wherewith the City and Fort of Bryſack ſhould have beene relieved together with all the wagons that belonged thereunto, which
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:16041:11"/> were in all 1000 in number. 3 That his Highneſſe hath taken from the Goetziſh and Savelliſh, all their baggage, namely 2000 Wagons and Carts, amongſt which were many faire Coaches, with a very rich booty, and eſpecially the Chaunceries and letters of both the Generall Field-Marſhals. 4 That his High<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe hath taken from them 80 Standards <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nd En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſignes, amongſt which were 7 of Generall Field-Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhall <hi>Goetz,</hi> his Life Regiment of Curraſſiers, which are very faire, and embroydered with ſilver and gold, and of other Regiments of Curraſſiers, were likewiſe found divers ſtandards. 5 That not onely above 1500 men of the Imperiall and Bavarian Army were ſlaine upon the place of fight, but alſo a great number of them chaſed into the River of Rhine and drowned: many yeelded upon diſcretion, and tooke ſervice un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der Duke <hi>Bernhard</hi> of Weymar: many were taken priſoners; and in a word, this brave Army, which conſiſted altogether of the ancient Regiments, at leaſt 12000 effective ſtrong, was ſo diminiſhed and diſper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, that as above ſaid, not above 2500 men of horſe and foot, came againe to their Generals, but how ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny wounded and hurt men are amongſt them, is not yet knowne. The Imperiall Field-Marſhall, <hi>Duc de Savelly,</hi> was ſhot into his backe, and narrowly eſca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ped. Colonell <hi>Seneſchall</hi> is taken priſoner, Colonell <hi>Meuſell,</hi> Colonell <hi>Hagſhauſen,</hi> Colonell <hi>Sales,</hi> who commanded the Briſigelliſh: Colonell <hi>Stephan Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bert,</hi> who commanded the Tylliſh: and Colonell <hi>de Puis,</hi> who commanded the Eppiſh Regiment, as alſo
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:16041:12"/> Colonell <hi>Limpach,</hi> and as it is generally beleeved, Colonell <hi>Edelſtett</hi> are ſlaine: five Lievetenant Colo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nels are taken priſoners, and at leaſt ſixe or ſeven ſlaine. Of Sergeant Majors were but three taken pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoners, but how many of them (as alſo of Captaines of horſe, Captaines of foot, Lievetenants, Standard<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bearers, Ancients, and other under Officers) were ſlaine, it is not yet perfectly knowne, although a great number of them are known, and eaſily may be gueſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed at by the precedent relation. Sergeant Major <hi>Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vario</hi> was buried at Overkerk, beſides other officers: and it is certaine that a great number of the Imperiall Officers are taken priſoners, even the Roſich Regi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment alone hath taken above 100. amongſt which the meaneſt are quarter-maſters; but the reaſon why the whole number of all the Regiments could not be drawn together and here named, is, becauſe the Regi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tinued together no lo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ger, but one whole day, but were partly by his Highneſſe, D. <hi>Bernard</hi> of Wey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mar commanded to purſue further after the enemy, and the moſt part of them ſent here and there into their quarters for the better conveniency of getting ſorrage for the horſes. His Highneſſe Duke <hi>Bernard</hi> of Weymar in this great and violent re-encounter, hath loſt on his ſide fourteene Enſignes, and eight Standards, two Majors, as namely Major <hi>Weyerſheim</hi> of the Tupadelliſh Regiment of horſe, and Major <hi>Vitzthumb</hi> of the Hatſteiniſh Regiment of foot, toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther with eight or nine Captaines of horſe and foot, and certaine under Officers, as alſo about 500 com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:16041:12"/> Horſemen and Souldiers, whoſe number was ſo largely ſupplyed and made up againe by the priſoners, that tooke ſervice willingly, that, as it was openly ſeene, the greater part of his High<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſes Regiments of Foote marched off from the place of fight certaine 100 men ſtronger then they were, when they went thither.</p>
            <p>The Imperialliſts in their retreate carryed a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way priſoners as above ſaid Generall Major <hi>Tupa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pell,</hi> Lieutenant Colonell <hi>Ruht</hi> of the Vorbufiſh Regiment, foure Captaines of Horſe, and three or foure Captaines of Foote, together with certaine Lieutenants, Standard bearers and Ancients, which within few daies ſhall bee redeemed againe by ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>change. And on his Highneſſe ſide in this firſt oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſion hath beene wounded moſt dangerouſly, Colonell <hi>Rotenhan</hi> a valiant Souldier, Lieutenant Colonell Rhinegrave <hi>Iohn Lodowick,</hi> Lieutenant Colonell <hi>Fleckenſtein,</hi> Major <hi>Roſa,</hi> Major <hi>Preſtin,</hi> but now, God bee thanked, they are all without danger of their lives, Colonell <hi>Roſa,</hi> and Colonell Count <hi>William Otto</hi> of Naſſaw have likewiſe beene ſhot, notwithſtanding they did not leave their Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice, but ſtill kept on Horſeback, and performed their ſervice: On Teueſday following being the 31 of Iuly his Highneſſe, Duke <hi>Bernhard</hi> of Wey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mar cauſed firſt of all thoſe Souldiers, which were ſlaine of his Army, as alſo all the chiefe of the enemies Officers, that could bee knowne to bee orderly buried.</p>
            <pb n="24" facs="tcp:16041:13"/>
            <p>In like manner his Highnes gave order, that provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſhould be made, that for the hurt and wounded, &amp; they were lodged in ſeverall places, afterwards he gave to the Souldiers for their refreſhment all the Wagons which were taken, together with all the proviſion in them, and ſent for all his Baggage to be brought unto him from Mohlburg upon the place of fight: On wedneſday morning being the 1. 11 of Auguſt, (to the praiſe and glory of God, who had granted ſo glorious a victory by the whol Army) a ſolemne Faſt of thankſgiving, was kept where the Hymne, Prayer, and the Annunciation of the bleſſings of the moſt High God did ſound a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout through the whole Campe, by every Regi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment ſeverally: And with his Highnes, were pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent all the Colonels and chiefeſt Officers, and to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether with Him they ſung hartily the 124 Pſalme: If God had not bin on over ſide &amp;c. afterwards af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter the hearing of the word of God, hee preſented himſelfe upon his knees under the open sky, and by ſpeciall praiers gave hearty thankes unto God Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mightie, and thereupon <hi>Te Deum Laudamus</hi> was joyfully ſounded, and with all ſubmiſſion were pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſented unto his Highneſſe, by every Regiment par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticularly, the Standards and Enſignes, which they had obtained, and did hang them up before his Tent, which (being many new and faire Standards and Enſignes) was very ſtately and ſumptuous to looke upon. After all this his Highneſſe firſt of all cauſed to bee diſcharged all the Cannons as well
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:16041:13"/> his owne, as alſo thoſe which hee had taken from his enemie, and then all the Horſemen and Muſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quetiers diſcharged twiſe in a faire order, and thus this generall feaſtivall day of joy was concluded. We heartily pray God Almighty to bleſſe this vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctory according to his Highneſſes owne words, praiers and hearty wiſhes, that it may tend to the glory and praiſe of Gods holy Name, for a gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall, firme and conſtant peace of our deare native Countrey, and to the redeeming and refreſhing of many diſtreſſed and oppreſſed Chriſtians. Amen, Amen.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="26" facs="tcp:16041:14"/>
            <head>FROM THE CAMPE BEFORE <hi>BRISACK,</hi> the 19. or 29. of September, 1638.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>T being noiſed in the Camp that ſome hundreds of Crabats, with certaine buſhels of meale behind them upon their horſes (were upon a deſigne, and on the way to get into <hi>Briſacke:</hi>) all paſſages were blocked up, and carefully watched, that they cannot eaſily ſteale into the town: we labour hard to fortifie the Campe on this ſide of the Rhine: namely, betwixt Hechen Helhing, and Iringh, as farre as the ſhip bridge: the trenches are in full defence (betwixt the French and high Dutch quarter) by twelve Redoubts, which are all well fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhed with Cannon proviſion and ammunition in the ſconces, which are thirteen in number, are made
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:16041:14"/> 
               <hi>Backhohſe,</hi> furnace, and other works. In a word, his Highneſſe the Duke <hi>Bernard</hi> of Weymar, takes great paines to get the City for the Crowne of <hi>France.</hi> Here in the Camp we have abundance of all manner of proviſion. And his Highneſſe Duke <hi>Bernard,</hi> cauſes the ſouldiers and labourers to worke day and night in the approaches. The ſouldiers that labour, receive eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry night 25 ſtivers a piece, and the Boores 10 ſtivers. The other day was brought into the Campe from <hi>Newburg,</hi> two great Morter pieces, and foure great pieces of ordnance, every one of them carrying a bul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>let of twelve pound, and yeſterday there was brought hither foure demy Canons. The beſieged ſhoot fierce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly out of the towne, becauſe they are well provided of ammunition, but hitherto they have done but lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle harme with their artillery. The fugitives that come to us out of <hi>Briſacke,</hi> relate unanimouſly that the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſion which was brought laſt into the towne, is al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt eaten up, for the towne cannot ſpend l<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſſe then 25 Multers of corne every weeke. They relate alſo that every ſouldier receives no more then halfe a pound of bread a day: of Cattell they have no want. Yeſterday nine of our horſemen went cloſe to the Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of <hi>Briſacke,</hi> and brought with them out of the pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſture 62 Beefes, and 13 horſes. We likewiſe have in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tercepted a Spy, who came with letters from the Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perour, (from Prague in Bohemia) unto Generall Major <hi>Reynaker,</hi> Governour in the City of Briſacke.</p>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="28" facs="tcp:16041:15"/>
               <head>Stransburgh the <hi>20</hi> or <hi>30</hi> of Sept.</head>
               <p>THe City of Briſacke is now round about beſie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged, ſo that now no man can get in, or come out without great danger of being taken or ſlaine. Freſh men are ſent from the Duke of Longe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ville, and more are expected daily: the Imperiall Field-Marſhall <hi>Goetzs</hi> lyes now at Villenghen, and the Duke <hi>de Savelly</hi> at Heilbrun. Duke <hi>Bernard</hi> hath taken the Village of Piſen into his trenches, becauſe the Crabats that laſt got into Briſacke, came that way. The head quarter of the Imperiall Field-Marſhall <hi>Goetz</hi> is at Eſhingen, four leagues from Briſack, where he doth intrench himſelfe for feare of being ſurprized by Duke <hi>Bernard.</hi> The moſt part of Duke <hi>Bernards</hi> Horſe lay in the Munſter Valley, foure leagues from Briſacke, and have brought great ſtore of proviſion (from the Swartzwold, <hi>alias</hi> Blackwood) and laid it into Fryburg.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="29" facs="tcp:16041:15"/>
               <head>Saint German <hi>22</hi> of Sept. <hi>2</hi> of October.</head>
               <p>THe Spaniſh forces have taken the Caſtle of Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mara, not farre from Caſſell, and have beſieged Roſigeau. The Dutcheſſe of Savoy hath deſired ayde and aſſiſtance of his Majeſty the King of France, or elſe ſhe ſhould be forced to come to an agreement with the Spaniard: wherefore his Majeſty the King hath ſent her in money 400000 pound.</p>
               <p>The Duke <hi>Charles</hi> of Lorraigne makes preparati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons for the reliefe of Briſacke, wherefore order is gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven by his Majeſtie the King, that divers troops ſhall be ſent to Duke <hi>Bernard</hi> of Weymar, to reinforce his Army. Monſieur <hi>Belleford</hi> with 400 horſe, and 1200 foot is marching toward the French County. And Colonell Gaſſion with foure Regiments towards Lor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raigne. Monſieur <hi>Hallier</hi> (as ſoone as Chaſtilett is for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tified, and the workes repaired) with 6000 horſe and foot is to follow him, and by the way is to cleare the Dukedome of Lorraigne, and to ſuccour Duke <hi>Ber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nard</hi> of Weymar. In a word, the moſt part of the French forces are going towards Briſgow.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="30" facs="tcp:16041:16"/>
               <head>Paris the <hi>22</hi> of Septemb <hi>2</hi> of Octob.</head>
               <p>DVke <hi>Bernard</hi> of Weymar hath ſent one of his Pages to his Majeſtie the King, and deſires ſuccour. The Cardinall <hi>Richelieu</hi> is at Saint Germains, and hath ſaluted the Queene and her Son, and this day he is expected here. The other day Count <hi>Henry</hi> of Naſſaw arrived here to congratulate their Majeſties the King &amp; the Queen in the name of his Highneſſe the Prince of Orange. The Lord of Bredrode is likewiſe expected to congratulate their Majeſties, the King and the Queene, in the name of the Lords States. Yeſterday the Ambaſſadors of the Crowne of Sweden, Genoa, and the Popes Nuntio have congratulated the Queene. The Lord <hi>Knyt</hi> is treating here with the King concerning the Lords States.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="31" facs="tcp:16041:16"/>
               <head>Antwerp the <hi>30</hi> of September, the tenth of October.</head>
               <p>FRom Lisbon the eighteenth or twenty eight of Auguſt is written, that in the harbour at Vien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>na and Porta Port, arrived the fourth or four<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teenth, and fifth or fifteenth of the ſaid moneth, 23 ſhips, with nine or ten thouſand cheſts of Sugar, and two hundred thouſand Rials, with other commodi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, which came from Rio dell Genuo. It was two yeares growth of the Sugar: five thouſand Cheſts more are expected from the Bahie Todos los Santos within few dayes. And they write, that the fleet ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed for Braſile, ſhall goe to Sea within two or three weekes, being 38 Sayle, amongſt which are five and twenty or ſixe and twenty well manned ſhips, but how many ſouldiers they are to carry thi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, is diverſly ſpoken of: ſome write of five thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand, others eight thouſand Souldiers and Mariners, but eſteemed unexpert men. As ſoone as the Fleet is gone to Sea, all the ſhips that are ſtayed there, ſhall be ſet free againe. The Spaniſh Army in Italy hath laid a bridge over the River of Seſia, neere Bremio, and an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>other over the River of Poe. The halfe of the Spaniſh Army lyes about Pomaro, and the reſt is gone towards Aigni to beſiege Alba.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="32" facs="tcp:16041:17"/>
               <head>Fluſhing the <hi>1</hi> or <hi>11</hi> of October.</head>
               <p>SInce my laſt letter, Captaine <hi>Iohn Williams</hi> hath brought in hither a Caravell, which came from Bahie Todos los Santos, which hath in her two hundred and ſixty cheſts of Sugar, a great number of Hides, a good quantity of Brazill wood, with other commodities.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="33" facs="tcp:16041:17"/>
               <head>Lower Saxony, the <hi>3</hi> or <hi>13</hi> of October.</head>
               <p>HIS Excellencie Generall <hi>Bannier</hi> lies about Drubenſea, with the greater part of his ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my. His troupes are to take their Winter quarter in the lower Pomerania. The Branden<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>burgiſh forces have plundred of their owne Cities Betzaw, Bernaw, and Landsberg. Thoſe of Berlin fearing they ſhould be ſerved in like manner, cauſe every night an hundred and ſixty ſoldiers to watch. The Sickneſſe is hot in the Brandenburgiſh campe and in the countrey there is great miſery.</p>
               <p>The ſeventeenth or twenty ſeventh of Septem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber his Imperiall Majeſty went from Brundis to Leutmaritz, to conferre there with the Elector of Saxony.</p>
               <p>The Prince Elector Palatine with his and the Swediſh troupes lies now before Lemgow, which he fiercely batters, and hath brought before it foure Morter pieces, and it is thought that the city will not be able to hold out long.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="34" facs="tcp:16041:18"/>
               <head>Amſterdam the ſixth or ſixteenth of October.</head>
               <p>IN the Texell lye ready foure ſhippes which are bound for Braſile, which carry over with them foure hundred and fifty land ſouldiers, and two great ſhippes likewiſe which are bound for Ginny.</p>
               <p>The army of his Highneſſe the Prince of Orange is broken up this weeke from the Grave, and gone into garriſon. And the other day his Highnes the Prince of Orange is ſafely arrived at the Hague.</p>
               <p>The valiant Ritmaſter <hi>Crook,</hi> while that the Car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinal Infant lay about Venlo, hath don great harme to the Spaniards, and brought many horſes into our Campe.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>From Frankfort the ſeventh or ſeventeenth of October it is written,</head>
               <p>THat the Weymeriſh Generall Commiſſio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner going from the Campe towards Baſill, is taken priſoner by an Imperiall party that was abroad that way.</p>
               <p>The Dunkirkers are now at ſea, the Hollanders are purſuing after them, and hath already taken two of their ſhips.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="35" facs="tcp:16041:18"/>
               <head>Venice the one and twentieth of September, or firſt of October.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>DOn Franciſco di Melo</hi> with the Spaniſh army intended to paſſe the river of Poneor Villa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gio, to make an invaſion into Montferrat: but the French and Savoy troupes lay in waite for them in an advantagious place, and gave them ſuch entertainement that they were forced to retyre and leave their bridge behind them.</p>
               <p>The Gallies of Malta have met with ſix Turkiſh Gallies of Rhodes, ſunke foure of them, and taken two; but two of the Maltaza Gallies were ſunke likewiſe in the fight.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Baſill the two and twentieth of September or ſecond of October.</head>
               <p>DVke <hi>Bernard</hi> of Saxon Weymar cauſeth the Labourers to worke hard about the circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vallation before Briſacke, and hath cut downe a great part of the wood on this ſide the Rhine; and to ſecure the bridge he hath raiſed neer unto it two Ravelins, and likewiſe a royall ſconce.
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:16041:19"/> The circumvallation is three houres going in the round, with deepe moats and breaſt workes, which in ſome places are ſixteene foot thicke.</p>
               <p>Sixe dayes agone the Cannons were mounted upon all the batteries, and played fiercely upon the beſieged. His army is victualled from Colmar Benfield, Strausburg, and the wood Cities, and from the blacke Forreſt the forrage and cattell are brought into the Campe. The moſt part of the French troupes are taken out of the campe and put into garriſon into Freyburg and other places; and the high-Dutch are brought out of the garriſons to ſupply their places. Many houſes and butts are built in the quarters, and a great Magazine is ere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted; whereby ſome gueſſe that Briſacke will hold out yet a long time. Colonell <hi>Roſa</hi> with ſixe Regi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments is gone through the wood towards New<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtat and Villengen, to viſit the Imperialiſts in their quarters.</p>
               <p>Colonell <hi>Berenhalt</hi> is freed from his impriſon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment by redemption: and the Marqueſſe of Dour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lach and Paderburg is freed from this world by death at Strausburg. Of the French ſuccours two thouſand men are arrived in this Biſhoprick, and in Delſperger valley the old garriſons of Mompel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard follow; inſomuch that Duke <hi>Bernard</hi> of Wey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mar (as it is thought) will receive an accrue &amp; ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cor of 12000 men.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="37" facs="tcp:16041:19"/>
               <head>Villingen the <hi>26</hi> of September, or ſixth of October.</head>
               <p>THe Imperiall field Marſhall <hi>Goetz</hi> with his Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my lies round about Ravensbergh, and hath drawne together in haſte all his horſe and foot, and hath brought together ten regiments.</p>
               <p>Generall major <hi>Lamboy</hi> and Colonell <hi>Wael,</hi> with foure thouſand men which will be here within ten or twelve dayes are to joyne with him.</p>
               <p>The twentieth or thirtieth of September the Dutcheſſe of Bavaria was brought to bed of another ſonne, who was chriſtened <hi>Maximilian Philippus Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ronimus.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="38" facs="tcp:16041:20"/>
               <head>Saint Germaine the <hi>29</hi> of September, or ninth of October.</head>
               <p>THe Admiral of Burdeaux for want of proviſion hath betaken himſelfe to Belſle. The Duke de Valetta Monſieur <hi>Grammont</hi> and others are expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted here to bring the information, who was in the fault that the ſiege before Fontarabie was raiſed. The government of Guyen is given to the Prince of Conde, and hath now abſolute authority to diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe of the warres in thoſe parts. His Majeſty the King hath ſent from Paris to Guyenne foure hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred thouſand pound. The Duke of Longueville hath order and command to hinder the victualling and reliefe of Briſacke from Lorraine ſide, and to ſend all needfull aſſiſtance to Duke <hi>Bernard</hi> of Weymar: foure Regiments conſiſting of two thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand men, are paſſed through the dominion of Berne and Delſpenger Vallie, under the command of Monſieur <hi>Roque,</hi> and gone to the Camp before Bri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſack. His Majeſtie the King hath likewiſe ſent to Duke <hi>Bernard</hi> Weymar, foure hundred thouſand pound.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="39" facs="tcp:16041:20"/>
               <head>Frem the Camp before Briſack the <hi>30</hi> of September, or <hi>10</hi> of October.</head>
               <p>THe circumvallations about this City, was fini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed ſeven dayes agone, conſiſting of twenty roy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all Sconces, and a great many of Redouts, with deep and wide Moats, and double Paliſadoes, in ſuch a form the like was hardly ever ſeen in Germany in any ſiege. Of victuals we have no want, bread we have in abun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dance, a pound of fleſh is ſold in the Campe for three pence, a quart of wine for foure pence: Geeſe, all ſorts of fowle, Salt, Bacon, Cheeſe, and other proviſions for the mouth, are bought at a reaſonable rate. The firſt of this moneth, Colonell <hi>Roſa</hi> went from the Blackwood into Vibres valley, and the Count of Naſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaw towards the Munſter valley, to viſit the Imperi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aliſts in their quarters, which intrench themſelves be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twixt Hohenwiel and Waldſhut; it ſeemes that they ayme at Lauffenberg, to make a diverſion. The City of Kentzingen, Duke <hi>Bernard</hi> of Weymar hath bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned downe, pulled downe the wals, and brought the materials of the ſaid City into the Campe, to build houſes and huts, it ſeemes as if a new City were built about Briſacke. The Duke of Longeville hath taken by aſſault Chamnitz. The third of this moneth, Mon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſieur <hi>le Motte,</hi> with 6000 foot, and 4000 horſe is mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched through the Biſhopricke of Baſill, and is expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted here to morrow. Colonell <hi>Shonbeck</hi> with 200
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:16041:21"/> Muskettiers, hath taken the little ſconce before Bri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſack, which lyes upon an Iland, in which hee found two pieces of Ordnance, each carrying a bullet of 6 pound, and three pieces of 12 pound bullet: the beſie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged in two dayes made upon it above 200 Cannon and demy-cannon ſhot, upon which we made a falſe alarum (to draw them out of the towne) made ſhew as if we would forſake the Sconce, but the beſieged found the contrary, for they were in great confuſion chaſed into the Rhine. The great Sconce neare the City is at this preſent likewiſe fiercely battered: as ſoone as we have maſtered the ſame, then we can with eaſe ruinate the bridge before Briſacke. Duke <hi>Bernard</hi> of Waymar is reſolved to fight againe another battell, if the Duke of Lorraine (who is at Than) with ſome thouſands of his owne men, and aſſiſted with the Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perialiſts, to aſſault the Duke <hi>Bernard</hi> on both ſides of the Rhine. Here at this preſent are the French Am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baſſadour, Monſieur <hi>Molliand,</hi> the Engliſh Reſident <hi>Fleminge,</hi> Generall Major <hi>Erlach,</hi> a Lord of Rhelin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gen, which treat upon weighty matters with Duke <hi>Bernard.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="41" facs="tcp:16041:21"/>
               <head>Lien the <hi>30</hi> of Septemb. <hi>10</hi> of Octob.</head>
               <p>THe Prince of Conde hath accuſed the Marſhall <hi>de Valette</hi> to be the occaſion of the loſſe at Fonta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rabie, alledging that hee did not aſſault the Spaniſh Succours, rather obeying his father the Duke of Eſper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nons co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mand, then the ſervice he ſhould have done; and this, becauſe he was diſcontented, that the gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall command which the Prince of Conde had, was not given unto him: wherefore his Majeſty, the King hath commanded <hi>Eſpernon</hi> to retire to his houſe, and the Marqueſſe <hi>de Valette</hi> ſummoned to appeare at the Court.</p>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="42" facs="tcp:16041:22"/>
            <head>SOME PASSAGES OVT OF THE <hi>NO<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>remberg</hi> Aviſoes, of the moneth of October, from <hi>Baſil.</hi>
            </head>
            <div type="part">
               <head>From the Camp before Briſack.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Hat the Imperiall Field-Marſhall <hi>Goetz,</hi> and Generall Major <hi>Lam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boy,</hi> the 11 or 21 day of this mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth, with 5000 horſe, and 8000 foot, and 12 pieces of Ordnance, broke up from Kirckhoſen, and marched towards Briſack, and preſented themſelves about the length of two Canon ſhots from the Weymariſh Campe, made three ſhots out of demy-Canons: whereupon thoſe of Briſacke, with three Canon ſhots anſwered; on Friday mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning the Imperialiſts with their Artillery approach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed,
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:16041:22"/> and at night 1000 foot, and certaine 100 Curraſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers carrying along with them great canon baskets, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended to aſſault a Sconce below Briſacke, but being there was a cleare Moone-ſhine night, they were bea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten off with ſmall ſhot. Vpon Sunday, being the 14 or 24 of this moneth, the Goetziſh Army aſſaulted the two upper Sconces, whereof one lay in the wood, and the other about Duke <hi>Bernards</hi> Rhine-bridge, and they were faine to wade through a moat and ditch above the middle, afore they could come neere the Sconce, yet at laſt they maſtered it, and put all the Scots that lay in it to the ſword, and thus maſtered the firſt bridge, which lay over an arme of the Rhine, and thereupon, two Imperiall ſquadrons about 1600 ſtrong, paſſed upon the head bridge of the Rhine, and threw off a part of it, leſt they ſhould be ſurprized and over-haſtened; notwithſtanding Duke <hi>Bernard</hi> of Weymar commanded thitherwards Colonell <hi>Shon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beck,</hi> with certain Regiments of horſe and foot, which immediately with boords and other materials, repai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red the Bridge again, and although the Goetziſh Muſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kettiers gave fierce fire upon them, yet at laſt they were beaten backe, many of them were drowned in the moat, and the reſt almoſt all ſlaine and taken pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoners, inſomuch that of thoſe 1600 men, very few eſcaped. In the meane time the Weymariſh forces un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the command of Monſieur <hi>de Guebrian,</hi> did beat the Goetziſh Muskettiers out of the next Sconce that lay in the Wood, and recovered againe the lower Sconce, but the upper Sconce, the Goetziſh forces
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:16041:23"/> kept ſtrongly guarded till night: but when Duke <hi>Ber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nard</hi> of Weymar commanded againſt it at night a Lievetenant with certaine troops of horſe and foot. He found the Sconce open and forſaken, inſomuch that the Goetziſh at night leaving behinde them 1600 dead, and certaine 100 wounded &amp; priſoners, amongſt which are ſaid to be 26 Captaines, broke up and mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched towards Freyburg, which place they ſummoned, yet they would not ſtay there, but marched towards Offenburg. Colonell <hi>Golling,</hi> together with many o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Officers, was ſlaine in this aſſault: on the Wey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mariſh ſide, Colonell <hi>Leſle</hi> is either ſlaine, or taken priſoner; Colonell <hi>Shonbeck</hi> was ſhot through the ſhoulder, and many of the ſouldiers were likewiſe ſlaine: yeſterday Duke <hi>Bernard</hi> of Weymar hath like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe taken the <hi>Iacobs</hi> Sconce and Mill Sconce, inſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>much that Briſack is now in extreame danger, out of which they ſhoot very fiercely.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Venice the <hi>29</hi> of Octob. and <hi>9</hi> of Novemb.</head>
               <p>AT Conſtantinople upon the command of the great Turke, the Venetian Ambaſſadour there is arreſted, and is watched at Pera by 200 Ianitſars, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe the Venetians have aſſaulted the Barbary Gal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lies in the harbour at Valona, wherefore this Signory is preparing &amp; making ready againſt the next Spring, above 100 Galleyes, beſides the Gallions and other ſhips.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="45" facs="tcp:16041:23"/>
               <head>Leipſig the <hi>27</hi> of Octob. or <hi>7</hi> of Novem.</head>
               <p>FRom the Marquiſate of Brandenburg is written, that the Imperiall Army is marching againe to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards Domitz: the Ship-bridge is likewiſe carried thi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther from Werben, and the Luneburgiſh troops about 4000 ſtrong, are likewiſe gone towards Domitz, and certaine Saxon Regiments under the command of Field-marſhall <hi>Marazini,</hi> are likewiſe marching to the Gallaſhiſh Army, inſomuch that the ſaid Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my will be reinforced with nine or ten thouſand freſh ſouldiers to oppoſe Generall <hi>Bannier,</hi> who is gone again from the River of Elve, towards the Dukedome of Mecklenburg, where hee maſtereth all the ſtrong places. Colonell <hi>Slangh</hi> hath likewiſe ſummoned the Warmunder Sconce, but the Governour in it refuſeth to ſurrender it.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Collen the <hi>25</hi> of Octob. the <hi>4.</hi> of Novemb.</head>
               <p>LAſt Sunday a great fire happened in the City of Orſoy, which burned down almoſt halfe the Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, and did great harme, and about 39000 Cheeſes, which belonged to ſhippers, &amp; all the matches for the garriſon was burned, inſomuch that they were to be provided againe from Rhinberck in all haſte.</p>
               <p>The Hatzfieldiſh troops lay yet ſtill in the Biſhop<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ricke of Oſnabrugge, and refreſh themſelves. Gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall Major King hath commanded abroad, 1000 horſe
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:16041:24"/> to d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ry them, which lighted upon foure Imperiall Companies, totally routed and diſperſed them, and tooke from them two Standards. In the Biſhopricke of Bremen have been taken up 2000 ſouldiers for the Prince Elector Palatine, which are already marching towards Minden.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>From the Camp before Briſack, the <hi>18</hi> or <hi>28</hi> of Octob.</head>
               <p>MOnſieur <hi>de Turenne,</hi> and Colonell <hi>Shmidberger,</hi> have taken by aſſault from the Briſackers, a head Sconce, on which the chain hangeth, which is a great loſſe to the Briſackers, inſomuch that the beſieged do ſhoot ſo fiercely no more: one that came out of the City, had about him bread that was baked of branne and Acron ſhels, who being ſtrictly examined, confeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed that they had generally no other bread in the town, except the high Officers.</p>
               <p>The 16. 26. of this moneth, the Lorraine troopes maſtered the City of Enſiſheim, but the Caſtle holds out yet, and is well provided. The Weymariſh horſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men are gone againſt them to beat them out againe. Field-marſhall <hi>Goets</hi> intends to lay a bridge over the Rhine at Druſenheim.</p>
               <p>The other day an Eagle flew thrice about Duke <hi>Bernard</hi> of Weymars campe, as alſo over Duke <hi>Ber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nards</hi> own Tent, but at laſt he flew towards Freyburg: the meaning of it, God knowes.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Collen the <hi>26</hi> of Octob. the <hi>5</hi> of Novem.</head>
               <p>The Palatine &amp; Swediſh troops gather themſelves again very ſtrong about Minden and Oſnabrugge, and they are already ſtronger then they have been be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the battell: there come daily more freſh forces un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </p>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="47" facs="tcp:16041:24"/>
            <head>THE AVISOES OF <hi>HOLLAND.</hi>
            </head>
            <div type="part">
               <div type="section">
                  <head>Venice <hi>the</hi> 5. 15. <hi>of Octob.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">F</seg>Ive Spaniſh Gallies with many military inſtruments are arived at Savona. The Governours of An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tybo, Saint Margaretta &amp; Villa Franca are put in priſon by the King of France becauſe they kept correſpondence with the King of Spaine.</p>
                  <p>Certaine dayes ſince, <hi>Ducca di Saint Georgia</hi> with 33 companies of Horſe, ſurpriſed 600 French horſe-men at <hi>Rocca Civalera,</hi> ſlew 150 of them, tooke 60 priſoners, among which are ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny officers, got 500 horſes, and 80 Mules with 12000 crownes in ready money, the reſt fled to <hi>Felizzano.</hi> The next day after, the Count <hi>Gale<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>azzo
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:16041:25"/> Trizze,</hi> who intended to ſurpriſe another French quarter, was beaten off with loſſe of 200 men, and himſelfe was greatly wounded.</p>
                  <p>The Duke of <hi>Savoy</hi> is deceaſed at <hi>Turino,</hi> and his brother of 8 yeers of age, is very ſicke. The Turkiſh Prince lyes now before <hi>Babilonia,</hi> where the <hi>primo Vezier</hi> a great enemy to the Chriſtians is lately dead.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>Strasburg <hi>the</hi> 5. 15. <hi>Oct.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>At this inſtant we received aviſoes that <hi>Colo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nell Roſa, Callenback</hi> and others with 7. regiments are gone againſt the Duke of <hi>Lorraine:</hi> in the meane time Duke <hi>Bernhard</hi> of <hi>Weymar</hi> keepes a watchfull eye towards the Imperiall Army, which intends to aſſault him unawares, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore bread is given for 6 dayes, to be given to the Souldiers.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>Berlin <hi>the</hi> 6. 16. <hi>of Oct.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>We have been here in great danger, becauſe Generall <hi>Gallas</hi> did ſend his Baggage on this ſide of <hi>Vierbellin,</hi> and the <hi>Swedes</hi> lay about <hi>Fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stenlerg,</hi> but generall <hi>Gallas</hi> with his Army ſet himſelfe before the <hi>Dam</hi> neere <hi>Rubin</hi> upon the high ground, and entrenched himſelf there, and having behinde him the River of <hi>Nien,</hi> the Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my cannot well come at him, except he doe aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſault him in his advantage, Since it was feared
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:16041:25"/> that the Enemy would go towards <hi>Berlin,</hi> but now we receive Aviſoes that Generall <hi>Gallas</hi> is going away from <hi>Vierbellin,</hi> and that he takes his way towards <hi>Werbin.</hi> Our Brandenburgiſh troopes ſtay behinde, and lye yet entrenched neere <hi>Vierbellin.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>Hamborough <hi>the</hi> 10. 20 <hi>of Oct.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>The Imperiall Generall <hi>Gallas</hi> with his Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my is retiring towards <hi>Havelberg,</hi> and takes his way towards <hi>Kluckaw,</hi> and ſo towards the Wer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber Sconce, where a Ship-bridge is laid over the River of Elve. The <hi>Swediſh</hi> Generall <hi>Banni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er</hi> followeth him upon the foot and hath left behinde him all his Baggage and carrieth along with him the proviſion upon horſes and Aſſes, and being he marched ſo ſwiftly, no doubt is but he will overtake the Imperiall Generall. Some other <hi>Swediſh</hi> troopes have made an inva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion into the Dukedome of <hi>Luneburg:</hi> they ſhew as yet no hoſtility but ſeeke only the paſſage ward the River of Elve. Laſt Sunday the <hi>Swediſh</hi> Colonell Slaugh with certaine troopes is like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe arrived at <hi>Boytſenburg,</hi> and paſſed yeſterday morning with 15 great boats at <hi>Lawenburg</hi> over the River of Elve to joyne with the reſt of the <hi>Swediſh</hi> troopes there: they are all going to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards the <hi>Werber</hi> Sconce where the <hi>Magazine</hi> of the Imperialiſts is, inſomuch that the aforeſaid Generall <hi>Bannier</hi> perſues after the Imperialiſts
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:16041:26"/> on both ſides of the River of Elve, which reti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring in great confuſion, pillage all the places whereſoever they come, yea their Generalls owne Baggage. Colonell Yerſdorff is ſent by Generall <hi>Gallas</hi> to the Emperour to certifie him of the miſerable ſtate and condition of his troopes, deſiring withall a ſpeedy aide and aſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance, becauſe he hath not above 8000 men more of his owne Army: and the <hi>Brandenburgiſh</hi> Army is ſo much conſumed that it is not ſtrong above 1000 horſe, and 150 foot; and more then 1000 of the <hi>Brandenburgiſh</hi> ſouldiers are come over to the <hi>Swedes,</hi> and have taken ſervice under Generall <hi>Bannier.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>A Relation of the Battell betwixt the Prince Elector Palatine, and the Imperiall Generall <hi>Hatzfeld,</hi> fought the 7.17. of <hi>Octob.</hi> neere <hi>Vlota</hi> on the River of <hi>Weſar.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">H</seg>Is Highneſſe, the Prince Elector Palatine, and his brother Prince <hi>Robert,</hi> being joyned with the Swediſh Generall Major <hi>King,</hi> they brought together an Army of 5000. men, and came before the City of
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:16041:26"/> 
                  <hi>Lemgow</hi> the Metropolitane of the Earledome of <hi>Lippe,</hi> but after they had ſtraitly continued the Siege for certaine dayes together, the Imperiall Generall <hi>Hatzfeld</hi> drew together an Army of 6000 men and went to relieve it, wherupon the ſaid Prince Elector Palatine thought it beſt to leave the ſiege and ſent before him all his Bag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gage towards <hi>Vlota</hi> in the Earldome of <hi>Raven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſperg</hi> to be tranſported thence towards <hi>Minden.</hi> The Imperiall Generall <hi>Hatzfeld</hi> having recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved intelligence of it by ſome priſoners, mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched in all haſte to cut off the paſſage from them, and overtook the ſaid Prince Elector a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout 2 of the clocke in the afternoon neere <hi>Val<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dorp.</hi> The Palatine and <hi>Swediſh</hi> troopes fought in the beginning moſt valiantly, and put the Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perialiſts to flight, and with their horſemen purſued cloſe after them, whereupon the Duke of <hi>Luneburg</hi> who had not ſhewed the leaſt hoſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity againſt them heretofore, came with 1000 horſe, and 1000 foot betwixt the <hi>Swediſh</hi> and Palatine horſe and foot, and ſeparated them that they could not get together againe, and im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mediately thereupon the Imperialiſts turned a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain and aſſaulted the Prince Elector and <hi>Swedes</hi> horſe, and the Duke of <hi>Luneburg</hi> the foot, and ſo kept them off that they could not ſuccour the horſe, inſomuch that the horſe being entrapped were at laſt totally routed, and many of them ſlaine and taken priſoners, and many of the foot were chaſed into the River of <hi>Weſar</hi> and drow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned,
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:16041:27"/> and the Imperialiſts obtained 8 pieces of Ordinance, 2 mortering pieces, 20 enſignes, and 4 Standards. The certaine number of thoſe that were ſlain and taken priſoners, is not yet known; the report goes of fifteene hundred that were both ſlaine and drowned, and about 800 taken priſoners. Among the chiefeſt of the priſoners theſe are known namely Prince <hi>Robert,</hi> Lieute<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant Generall <hi>Ferars,</hi> the Lord <hi>Craven,</hi> Colonell <hi>Boy,</hi> Lieutenant Colonell <hi>Berovo</hi> of <hi>Wenge,</hi> Colo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nell <hi>Buſaid,</hi> Colonell <hi>Mulard,</hi> Lieutenant Colo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nell <hi>Loke,</hi> the younger <hi>King,</hi> and others. The Prince Elector Palatine himſelfe, and Generall Major <hi>King</hi> eſcaped and fled into <hi>Minden.</hi> On the Imperiall ſide is ſlaine the Generall Serjant Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jor Count Peter <hi>Goetz,</hi> Colonell <hi>Tyrelly,</hi> and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers. Prince <hi>Robert</hi> is ſhrewdly wounded, and the Lord <hi>Craven</hi> hath received 5 wounds.</p>
               <p>The laſt letters from Italy bring no other news but that the French and Savoyiſh troops have routed and defeated upon the borders of Savoy 3000 Spaniſh ſouldiers.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>From Saint Germaine <hi>the</hi> 13. 23 <hi>of Oct.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>THe Queen of Spaine is brought to bed of a daughter. His Majeſty the King of France hath ſent a new ſupply of money unto his Highneſſe Duke Bernard of Weymar,
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:16041:27"/> and upon the frontiers he provideth for thee maintaining of the Armies, and hath likewiſe laid up in ſtore a great ſumme of money for the continuation of the warre.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Aviſoes of Holland.</head>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>Alſatia the 17. 27. <hi>of Octob.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">D</seg>Uke <hi>Charles</hi> of Lorraine is arrived on this ſide of the Rhine, &amp; with five or ſix thouſand men paſſed <hi>Thun,</hi> carying along with him a great ſtore of Proviſion and Am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munition, with a full reſolution to bring it into <hi>Briſſack,</hi> and to relieve the ſaid Towne: But his Highneſſe Duke Bernhard of Saxon Weymar, for the preventing of his deſigne, broke up in all haſte with certaine 1000 men and went to meet him, and at laſt lighted upon him in the valley betwixt <hi>Enfiſhem</hi> and <hi>Thun,</hi> where he aſſaulted the ſaid Duke of Lorraine furiouſly, to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tally routed and defeated his Army, ſlew many of the Lorrainers, took from them all their Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nons, Baggage and Ammunition, and obtained in a ſhort time a glorious victory. Whereupon the aforeſaid Duke Bernhard of Saxon Wey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mar returned immediately back againe into the Camp before <hi>Briſsack,</hi> and by a ſucceſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>efull en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terpriſe
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:16041:28"/> without the loſſe of any man took the great Sconce together with the outmoſt bridge, which thoſe of Briſſack had on this ſide of the <hi>Rhine.</hi> In the meane time the Imperiall field<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>marſhall <hi>Goetz,</hi> Generall Major <hi>Lamboy</hi> and <hi>Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>etz</hi> with a ſtrong Army conſiſting of 14000 fighting men, thought likewiſe to try their for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tune on the other ſide of the Rhine towards <hi>Briſgaw</hi> and to relieve the ſaid City and Fort of <hi>Briſſack,</hi> and with great fury aſſaulted 4 ſeverall times our Sconces, and in the 5 aſſault they brought it ſo far that they tooke not only one Sconce, but alſo under favour of their Cannons brought a whole Regiment into the ſame; But his Highneſſe Duke <hi>Bernhard</hi> of <hi>Saxon Weymar</hi> aſſaulted the Enemy immediately with ſuch a fury and courage, that the Imperialiſts were preſently beaten againe out of the Sconce, inſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>much that the Imperiall General Major <hi>Lamboy</hi> loſt the moſt part of his forces there, at which he took great diſtaſte againſt Field marſhall <hi>Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>etz,</hi> becauſe the ſaid <hi>Lamboy</hi> gave the firſt onſet and thought to get great honour by it, and the other Field-marſhall <hi>Goetz</hi> did not in due time ſecond him, and by that meanes both the Gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ralls are now at variance, inſomuch that the ſaid Generall Major <hi>Lamboy</hi> will give none other aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſault, their faire and brave Cavallerie comes quite to nothing, they runne away in great num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers for want of forrage and victualls, and their horſes die likewiſe in great numbers. The pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoners
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:16041:28"/> relate that in 5 dayes they have not ſeen a piece of bread in their Campe; and it is certaine that their pockets were found full of crabs. The reſt of the Lorrain foot forces run dayly away in great numbers, and come over unto us.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>Benfeld <hi>the</hi> 14. 24. <hi>of Octob.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>Since the overthrow of the Duke of Lorraine, upon the <hi>Oxenfield,</hi> the 5. 15. of this moneth, the ſaid Duke of Lorrain, with the diſperſed troops, fled to <hi>Than.</hi> Certain Weymariſh Regiments fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed him upon the foot to ruinate the Wagons, which about 600. in number, were each of them loaden with 6. quarters of Meale, and left in the open field before <hi>Than.</hi> The moſt part of the Lor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raine foot fled into the wood, where they were at laſt forc'd to yeeld upon diſcretion. His horſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men ſuffered ſhrewdly, and were totally diſper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, and the Weymariſh obtained 12 peeces of Ordnance, ſmall and great: 34 Standards, and 20 Enſignes, Colonell <hi>Roſa</hi> only with his Regiment hath routed 3 of the Enemies Squadrons, and bea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten divers times through them. The Duke of Lor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raines owne horſe was got by Colonell <hi>Roſa's</hi> Page and brought into <hi>Colmar.</hi> The Duke of Lor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raine ſav'd himſelfe on foot through the wood. Monſieur <hi>Paſſampiere,</hi> 2 Colonells, both <hi>Mercy,</hi> and Colonell <hi>Famier,</hi> and 20 other officers are brought priſoners into <hi>Colmar.</hi> On our ſide is ſlain Colonell <hi>Wickerkeyme,</hi> and many wounded ſoul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diers are come into <hi>Colmar.</hi> In the mean time the Imperiall Field-marſhall <hi>Goetz</hi> aſſaulted likewiſe
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:16041:29"/> furiouſly at night the Campe of Duke <hi>Bernhard</hi> of <hi>Weymar,</hi> but was three times beaten off with the loſſe of many of his men, and retired 2 houers go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing from the Campe, where he lyes yet. The 6. 16 of this moneth, the beſieged ſallied forth very ſtrong, but after a ſmall skirmiſh they were chaſed backe againe into the Towne. The 18 of this moneth, triumphes were made at <hi>Colmar</hi> for the victory, and the 9. 19 of this moneth, here in this City.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>Boytzenburg <hi>the</hi> 16. 26 <hi>of Oct.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>After that the Imperiall Generall <hi>Gallas</hi> was broke up from his head quarter at <hi>Malchin,</hi> in great diſorder, his Excellence the Swediſh Generall <hi>Bannier</hi> followed him the 10. 20 of this moneth with the horſemen as farre as <hi>Witſtock, Perlebarg,</hi> and the River of <hi>Havell.</hi> The ſaid Generall <hi>Gallas</hi> hath left behinde him in the villages, and in the way many ſicke and tyred ſouldiers, and beſides he hath loſt neere upon 1500 men which were cut off from him in the purſuite. In the meane time Generall <hi>Bannier</hi> hath taken <hi>Lawenburg, Newmarck</hi> and this City of <hi>Boytzenburg, Guſtrow, Swerin,</hi> and other Cities and paſſages and ſtrongly guarded them. Here in this City lye 3 Swediſh Regi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, and at <hi>Lawenburg</hi> foure Regiments which have arreſted all Saxon and <hi>Brandenburgiſh</hi> ſhips, and here lay a bridge over the River of Elve to hinder that the Imperialiſts get no proviſion and ammunition from <hi>Hamborough.</hi> The Swediſh Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerall Major <hi>Polin</hi> with certaine Swediſh troops
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:16041:29"/> hath made an invaſion into the Dukedome of <hi>Luneburg,</hi> inſomuch that the City of <hi>Luneburg</hi> ſtands now in great danger and feare, and by all appearance neutrality will be denied to the Duke of <hi>Luneburg.</hi> At this inſtant we receive certaine Aviſoes that the Imperiall Generall <hi>Gallas</hi> being loath to expect the Swedes betwixt the Rivers of Havell and Elve is broke up againe, and tooke a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>long with him the Ship-bridge neere the Cloer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber-Sconce, and the moſt part of the proviſion, and is retired towards <hi>Sandaw</hi> into the Biſhoprick of <hi>Maydenburg,</hi> w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ere he intends to lay the Ship-bridge againe over the River of Elve to be the neerer to <hi>Salome</hi> and the Emperours hereditarie Countreys: whereupon his excellency Generall <hi>Bannier</hi> is likewiſe broke up from his head quar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter at <hi>Swerin,</hi> and takes his way directly towards <hi>Saxony,</hi> being fully reſolved to follow the Imperi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all Generall <hi>Gallas</hi> though it were into <hi>Bohemia,</hi> but ſome thinke that he will firſt of all aſſault the <hi>Werber</hi> Sconce to have a free paſſage over the Ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver of Elve. His Excell: General <hi>Bannier</hi> could not draw the Imperiall Generall <hi>Gallas</hi> to battaile in the purſuite. The Earle of <hi>Ridbery</hi> who with 15 Regiments led the avantguard, had expreſſe order to hazard no skirmiſh. The priſoners declare and certifie that the Gallaſſiſh army is in all not 12000 men ſtrong. At this preſent the City of <hi>Domitz</hi> is fiercely battered by the Swedes with 24 peeces of Ordnance. Many Swediſh officers are now at <hi>Hamborough,</hi> where they ſet themſelves out brave<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly,
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:16041:30"/> and by this breaking up of the Imperial Army, and the good ſucceſſe of the Swedes, the treaty of peace at <hi>Lubeck</hi> is quite broke off.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>Collen <hi>the</hi> 20. 30. <hi>of Oct.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>The Duke of <hi>Newburg</hi> hath taken up many officers, both of horſe and foot. It ſeemes that he intends to take up certaine 1000 men for the defence of his Countreys, but many feare that it will be for no good end, becauſe the report goes that the ſaid Duke of <hi>Newburg</hi> hath received at <hi>Bruſſells</hi> certaine 1000 Rix-Dollers for the levy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of thoſe men. Since the overthrow of the Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>latine Armie, the diſperſed repaire again towards <hi>Minden,</hi> where they keepe their Randevouze. The Imperialiſts have taken <hi>Wit<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>aeden,</hi> and ſeeke to deſtroy the Palatines Forces in all places.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>Furnelford <hi>the</hi> 21. 31 <hi>of Oct.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>Duke <hi>Bernard</hi> of <hi>Weymar</hi> hath taken <hi>de Novo</hi> a Sconce of the River of <hi>Rhine</hi> before <hi>Briſſack,</hi> in which he found three Pieces of Ordnance. The great Sconce being of great importance which lyes in the midſt of <hi>Rhine</hi> is likewiſe ſurrendred, whereupon he hath burned downe a great part of the bridge. The beſieged ſhoot continually fiercely into the Towne. The Imperiall Field-marſhall <hi>Goetz</hi> hath aſſaulted a great Sconce which lyes on the ſide of the <hi>Rhine</hi> upon a hill, but was beaten off by Colonell <hi>Moſer,</hi> and left behind him many dead men, and certaine 100 Cannon Baskets: notwithſtanding he makes great ſhow a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain as if he would aſſault the Camp on 3 places.
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:16041:30"/> And from <hi>Strasburg</hi> they write already that for certain houres together they heard terrible Shoo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting; what there paſſed, we ſhall ſhortly heare.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>Liepſich 20. 30 <hi>Octob.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>The Imperiall Generall Lord <hi>Rodolph</hi> Count of <hi>Marazini</hi> is now in pay of the Elector of Saxony, and made Field-marſhall of his forces, who went from hence this afternoone, and went into <hi>Luſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tia</hi> to draw there together the Saxon Regiments, and to joyne with the Imperiall Gallaſſiſh Army.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>Amſterdam <hi>Octob.</hi> 27. <hi>Nov.</hi> 6.</head>
                  <p>Yeſterday was ſeaven night the ſhip of the Lord Vice-admirall <hi>Wemmer</hi> of <hi>Berchem</hi> arrived in the Texell himſelfe, becauſe he was ſickely, came o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver land, having given the abſolute Command to his Lieutenant. <hi>Octob.</hi> 21. the Dunkerkes put to Sea with 14 men of warre, and 2 Fregats, our Admirall <hi>Adam Witten-wittenſe,</hi> which croſſed the Sea neere <hi>Gravelinge</hi> perſued them and met them in the Ocean, where 4 dayes together <hi>viz</hi> till <hi>Oct.</hi> 15. 25 they charged each other continually, but the laſt of thoſe nights being very darke, they loſt one another. It is thought that the Dunkerkes tooke their courſe towards the North, whither our Vice-admirall followeth them. This weeke here are arrived ſome ſhips, which came from Saint <hi>Huges,</hi> with letters from <hi>Lisbone,</hi> Dated <hi>Octob.</hi> 14. the contents whereof are theſe. The 7 of the laſt moneth the Portugall Fleet departed thence, conſiſting of 26 Sayle, of ſmall and great bottomes: the Spaniſh Fleet following 18. 28 of
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:16041:31"/> the ſame, which conſiſted of 19 ſtrong veſſels, both theſe are to meet at <hi>Capo verde,</hi> they carry 8000 Souldiers and Marriners under the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand of a Portugall <hi>Don Ferdinando Maſsas,</hi> who hath been Vice Roy of <hi>Goa,</hi> and their Admirall <hi>Franciſco d' Amello</hi> a ſtout Souldier. There is brought into Zealand, a Prize with 200. pipes of Canary wine. The Turks have taken two ſhips which were going from Holland to Saint Lucars, and another is burnt by miſchance. Laſt Munday, 4. ſhips arived in the Texell, from <hi>Fernambouck,</hi> by name, the <hi>Spoel-Iacht,</hi> the <hi>Black-Beare,</hi> the <hi>Tigre,</hi> and <hi>Empreſse,</hi> which brought about 3000. Cheſts of Sugar with them. Two dayes before arived in the Texell the ſhip <hi>Crom-ſteven,</hi> which came from <hi>Rio Grande</hi> with 26000000 l. of Brazile-wood, and brings news, that in the <hi>Capitania</hi> of <hi>Fernam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bouck,</hi> 16. <hi>Seignors d' Ingenios,</hi> and a Burgomaſter of <hi>Pariba</hi> are taken priſoners, which held corre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpondence with the Count <hi>d'Baniola,</hi> and that they have erected a great private Magazine to ſuccour the Spaniſh forces in time of neede.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>Baſill 5.15. <hi>Octob.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>Laſt Friday, Colonell <hi>Shmitberger</hi> took the half moone before the bridge at <hi>Briſſack,</hi> and burnt downe a great part of the bridge, maugre the garriſon which in vaine played fiercely upon him with their Demi-Cannons.</p>
                  <p>Yeſterday was ſevennight, when Duke Bern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hard went to prayers, an Eagle flew round about the Camp and the Dukes tent, as if it would have
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:16041:31"/> pearched there, yet afterwards it flew to the mountains; this was ſeen by all the Camp.</p>
                  <p>The Imperial Fieldmar: <hi>Gotz</hi> is paſſed the Rhine at <hi>Druſenheim,</hi> and the Duke <hi>Savelly,</hi> and Colonell <hi>Cappaun,</hi> who are to joyne with him at <hi>Germeſheim,</hi> to make a new adventure upon the Camp on this ſide the Rhine. The French ſuccours conſiſting of 4000, horſe and 2000, foot, is arived at <hi>Du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dell.</hi> In <hi>Briſſak</hi> there is ſaid to be ſo much treaſure, that if the Imperialiſts ſhould looſe it, they would eſteeme the loſſe greater then the loſſe of a King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>Hamburgh. Octob. <hi>30.</hi> Novemb. <hi>9.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>The Duke of Luneburgh having conferred with the King of Denmarke at <hi>Gluckſtadt,</hi> is returned to <hi>Hildeſheim,</hi> his troops are ſent to <hi>Gallas</hi> his Army. The City of <hi>Vecht,</hi> though the report was other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe, holds out ſtill. The Prince Elector, and Generall <hi>King,</hi> rally their forces, and reſolve a re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venge.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>Leipſich <hi>Novemb.</hi> 2. 12.</head>
                  <p>The Diet of the circle of upper Saxe is this day begun. Both Armies in Pomerania lie ſtill. The City of <hi>Witſtock</hi> is fired in divers places, and burnt downe to the ground.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>Collen <hi>Novemb.</hi> 1. 11.</head>
                  <p>The Hollanders are ſtill levying new forces. But the Prince of Orange reſolveth not to goe to field, without abſolute power to manage the war, and to fight a battell if there be opportunity.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <pb n="62" facs="tcp:16041:32"/>
                  <head>From the Camp before <hi>Briſſak</hi> Oct. <hi>25.</hi> No. <hi>4.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>Duke Bernhard hath intercepted letters dated at Briſſack <hi>Oct.</hi> 9. 19. in which the Governor com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaines that he hath not bread but for two dayes, and fleſh but for few: that the moſt part of his men, the officers eſpecially, are ſick, dead, run a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way, and diſcontented: that <hi>Aug.</hi> 26. he was pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſed reliefe within ſixe weeks, which time was expired above three weeks ſince; deſiring, that if things did not go well with him, he might not be blamed, he being already brought to extremity, that he durſt not write that which moſt troubled him; yet notwithſtanding he would do his beſt to hold the place, and not ſhew himſelfe of leſſer courage then thoſe of <hi>Hermenſtein.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>From the Camp before <hi>Briſſack</hi> No. <hi>9.</hi> new ſtile</head>
                  <p>Duke Bernhard hath ſent a Trumpet to the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernour, and offered him honourable Conditions; adding, That if he ſtood out againſt reaſon, he could not take it well, nor would he deal with him as with an honeſt Cavaliere. The anſwer we expect. By all apperance the Duke will aſſault the <hi>Eckelsberg,</hi> for which all the officers importune him, promiſing to doe their beſt indeavours.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>Inclingen Novemb. <hi>10.</hi> new ſtile.</head>
                  <p>Monſieur <hi>Feuquieres</hi> having blocked up <hi>Lune<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ville,</hi> and underſtood that the Duke <hi>de Savelle</hi> was on his way to march by <hi>Inclingen, Octo.</hi> 26. <hi>old ſtile,</hi> marched thitherward to meet him: But the Duke having intelligence of it, tooke his way towards <hi>Blaumont,</hi> whither <hi>Feuquiers</hi> followed him, en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quartering
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:16041:32"/> betwixt <hi>Arrecourt,</hi> &amp; <hi>Blaumont (Octob.</hi> 28.) into which place, <hi>Savelly's</hi> Infantrie and ſome troops of horſe were laid. <hi>Feuquieres</hi> immediate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly charged, routed and defeated them; made them yeeld upon diſcretion; tooke their waggons, 80 in number, loaden with Ammunition, and 3 barrels of money; and preſently ſurrounded the ſmall Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, and Caſtle of <hi>Blanckenbourg,</hi> wherein <hi>Savelly,</hi> and the reſt of the horſe lay. So that now the Duke is in a trap; there being no ſuccour to be ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pected, no proviſion there for his horſe, and men, and the place of no ſtrength. But at this inſtant we receive aviſoes, that the Duke with 30 horſe, is got out of the Towne, and eſcaped narrowly.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>From the Biſhoprick of <hi>Bremen.</hi> Nov. <hi>10. 20.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>700 Souldiers, Engliſh, Scots, and of other Nations, taken up by Colonell <hi>Valkener</hi> for the Prince Elector Palatine, thought to have mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched through the City of <hi>Bremen,</hi> but the Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrate would not ſuffer them, yet he granted them paſſage below the City over the <hi>Weſar.</hi> Our Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop underſtanding it, charged his ſubjects to let no man paſſe, who thereupon took up Armes and beat them backe to the gates of <hi>Bremen,</hi> where they lay two dayes without victuals, and at the laſt were faine to runne away, and ſhift for them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves. And now both the Biſhop, and the Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrate, require the Princes Colonels to bring no more forces that way, and to Countermand ſuch as be upon the way.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <pb n="64" facs="tcp:16041:33"/>
                  <head>Minden <hi>Novemb.</hi> 11. 21.</head>
                  <p>The Prince Elector Palatine is here ſtill, and by all appearance will winter here. Lieutenant Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerall <hi>King</hi> hath rallyed his troops, and put them into Gariſon to refreſh themſelves, with order to give no reſt to the Enemy. Colonell <hi>Coningsmark,</hi> hath done ſomething already, He hath aſſaulted, and defeated the Imperiall Reare-ward, taken di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers officers, and common men, which he hath brought into this City, with ſome Enfignes: o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther parties are abroad, which ſo fill our priſons with Imperialiſts, that it is thought they will not be able to abide long amongſt our Garriſons.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>From the Biſhoprick of <hi>Munſter.</hi> Nov. <hi>11. 21.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Hatzfeld</hi> hath taken <hi>Cloppenburg;</hi> and now batte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth <hi>Vecht;</hi> but by reaſon of the raine he cannot come neere it: His Souldiers in the Approaches ſtand above the knees in water. His greateſt peece is broken. All the Swediſh horſemen which lay about <hi>Oſnabrugge,</hi> are gone to <hi>Minden,</hi> to joyne with other troops there.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>
                     <hi>Hamburgh. Nov.</hi> 16. 26.</head>
                  <p>Nothing hath yet paſſed betwixt <hi>Banniere,</hi> and <hi>Gallas;</hi> only they lye cloſe together, and it is thought, will not part without blowes. <hi>Banier</hi> hath given money to his Cavaliers to buy new horſes, many of his old horſes, having died with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in few weeks.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="65" facs="tcp:16041:33"/>
            <head>A VISOES FROM <hi>NORIMBERG.</hi> A full declaration of the Battell be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twixt Duke <hi>Bernhard</hi> and the Duke of <hi>Lorrain.</hi>
            </head>
            <div type="part">
               <head>
                  <hi>From</hi> Baſill <hi>the</hi> 12. 22. <hi>Oct.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">D</seg>Uke <hi>Bernhard</hi> of <hi>Weymar</hi> having re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived intelligence that the Duke of <hi>Lorrain,</hi> Generall Sergeant Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jor <hi>Paſsampiere,</hi> and Generall Major <hi>Mercy,</hi> the 3. 13 of this moneth, with 6 Regiments of horſe, 5 peeces of Ordnance a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong which are 2 Demicannons, and 80 wagons loaden with proviſion was arrived about <hi>Than,</hi> he himſelfe in perſon in all haſte with 7 Regiments of horſe and 500 commanded muſqueteres, under the command of Colonell <hi>Shmitberger,</hi> 6 peeces of Ordnance each carrying a bullet of 6 pound,
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:16041:34"/> broke up and marched toward <hi>Than,</hi> &amp; the 5. 15 of this month about 10 of the clock in the morning, lighted upon the Duke of <hi>Lorraine</hi> betwixt <hi>Vfhott<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zen,</hi> and <hi>Sanheimeb,</hi> where he lay with his whole Army, which Duke <hi>Bernhard</hi> of <hi>Weymar</hi> immedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ately charged and eſpecially ſlanked upon the horſe from all places, and aſſaulted them with ſuch fury, that at laſt they were forced to leave the field in great diſorder and confuſion, leaving many dead, wounded, and priſoners behind them. The foot forces after the fight retired into a wood called <hi>Nunnenbruch;</hi> which wood, Duke <hi>Bernhard</hi> ſurrounded with the horſe, planted the Ordnance before it, and ſhot ſo fiercely into it, that many of the <hi>Lorrainers</hi> were ſlaine in it: of the reſt ſome hid themſelves, and ſome fled towards <hi>Than,</hi> Duke <hi>Bernhard</hi> having got all the <hi>Lorraine</hi> Can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nons, all the ammunition, wagons, and 23 Stan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dards. Generall Sargeant Major <hi>Paſsampiere,</hi> the Generall <hi>A'diutant,</hi> Lieutenant Colonell <hi>Fleeken<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtein,</hi> many Captaines of horſe, and other officers, are taken priſoners. What officers have been ſlain on the Weymariſh ſide, is not yet knowne; we heare only of Colonell <hi>Witterſheim.</hi> The Count of <hi>Naſſaw</hi> is ſhot into the Leg: Colonell <hi>Okem</hi> had only a touch of a Bullet, and the Earle of <hi>Witgen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtein</hi> was ſhot through the cheeke. After this vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctory, the French ſuccour conſiſting of 2000 men joyned with Duke <hi>Bernhard</hi> of <hi>Weymar,</hi> who im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mediately thereupon with his troops marched a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain into the Camp before <hi>Briſſack,</hi> becauſe Field-marſhall
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:16041:34"/> 
                  <hi>Goetz</hi> and Generall Major <hi>Lamboy</hi> had joyned together and arrived at <hi>Kirchhoffin</hi> betwixt <hi>Freyburg</hi> and <hi>N<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>wburg</hi> with 5000 horſe, and 7000 foot, 12 peeces of Ordnance and great ſtore of proviſion. The other day Duke <hi>Bernhard</hi> of <hi>Wey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mar</hi> commanded Colonel <hi>Shmitberger</hi> and Colonel <hi>Shonbeck</hi> with 2000 men, and many ſcaling lad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders to march on this ſide of the <hi>Rhine</hi> againſt the Sconce before <hi>Briſſack,</hi> which they aſſaulted with ſuch fury, that they tooke it without any remark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able loſſe, and obtained in it 10 peeces of Ord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance, and burned downe a great part of the <hi>Rhine</hi> bridge, and have ſo entrenched themſelves alrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy againſt the Sconce, that the beſieged can doe them no more harme with their Canons although for 2 dayes together they have made 1000 Canon ſhot out of the Towne upon the Sconce, but all was in vaine. Yeſterday 2000 ſacks with Oates, 1500 ſacks with Meale, 600 ſacks with Corne, 3000 loafes of bread were brought downe from above in 6 ſhips into the Campe before <hi>Briſsack.</hi> Laſt Friday when the battell was ended, Field-marſhall <hi>Goetz</hi> gave a furious aſſault at night upon Weymariſh Campe on this ſide of the Rhine, but he was ſo received by the Canons, that he was forced to retire back from the Camp an hour and a halfe's going. Saturday night the beſieged ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lied likewiſe forth very ſtrong, but after a long Skirmiſh they were beaten back againe. we have now ſeen again the third time a great fire, which is
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:16041:35"/> taken for a ſigne that the beſieged are in great di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtreſſe.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Brunſwick <hi>the</hi> 7. 17 <hi>of Octob.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>The Imperiall Lieutenant Generall <hi>Gallas</hi> with his troopes lyes now at <hi>Havelberg,</hi> and Generall <hi>Bannier</hi> in the Principallity of Saxon <hi>Lawenburg</hi> on the River of Elve, of whoſe Army certaine 1000 horſe have beene already on this ſide of the River of Elve, an<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> driven away much cattell out of the Dukedome of <hi>Luneburg,</hi> fired a whole vil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lage, and thereupon went backe againe with the bootie. Their intent is to lay a Ship-bridge over the Elve which the Duke of <hi>Luneburg</hi> intends to hinder. The <hi>Gallaſsiſh</hi> army when it broke up from <hi>Pomerania,</hi> becauſe of the deep waies and marraſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, hath left behind it divers great peeces of Ord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance which the Swedes got. The firſt of <hi>Novem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber,</hi> ſhall be a meeting in <hi>Leipſich,</hi> of the circle of upper and lower <hi>Saxonie,</hi> and the like ſhall be done in other circles, to conſult by what meanes the e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nemies of the ſacred Romane Empire may be op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Collen <hi>the</hi> 18. 28. <hi>of Octob.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>From <hi>Paderborne</hi> is written that the diſperſed Swediſh and Palatine troops gather themſelves againe about the River of <hi>Weſar.</hi> Thither are like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:16041:35"/> marching 4 Swediſh Regiments which have not been in the battell, as alſo thoſe Swediſh Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giments which lay at <hi>Sutterſea,</hi> Generall <hi>Picolomi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ni</hi> is now going into his winter quarters in the Countrey of <hi>Gulick.</hi> Some ſay that he is to go to Field marſhall <hi>Goetz.</hi> The Spaniſh Gariſon in <hi>Ker<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pen</hi> doth great harme, wherefore certaine <hi>Holland</hi> troops are likewiſe going towards the Countrey of <hi>Gulick.</hi> Foure dayes ago the <hi>Weymariſh</hi> have ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken the other Sconce on the <hi>Rhine.</hi> Colonell <hi>Shmitberger</hi> lyes now in the ſaid Sconce, and ſhot downe &amp; burned a great part of the other bridge. In the laſt battell of the <hi>Lorraine</hi> horſemen eſca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ped not 100. The foot forces runne away in great number. At <hi>Mulhauſen, Baſel</hi> and <hi>Newburg</hi> above 300 have taken ſervice under Duke <hi>Bernhard.</hi> At this inſtant we receive Aviſoes that the great Sconce which lyes in the midſt of the <hi>Rhine</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twixt the two bridges is likewiſe taken by the <hi>Weymariſh,</hi> which is of great importance.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>From the Campe before <hi>Briſſack</hi> the <hi>14. 24</hi> of Oct.</head>
               <p>This morning the Imperiall field-marſhall <hi>Goetz,</hi> and Generall Major <hi>Lamboy</hi> have made a furious aſſault upon the Sconces of our Camp be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the Ship-bridge above the city: and after that we had beaten them off 4 times in the 5 aſſault, they became Maſters of 2 Sconces and the Spip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bridge,
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:16041:36"/> and had got above 400 men upon the ſaid bridge: but they were ſo furiouſly aſſaulted by the Vicount of <hi>Turenne</hi> with his French troopes, that they were not only forced to forſake the bridge, but alſo one of the Sconces that they had taken. Almoſt all the Imperialiſts that were upon the bridge have beene knocked downe without mercy; and it is certaine that the enemy in thoſe aſſaults hath loſt above 1000 men, and we have taken priſoners 5 Captains, and Colonell <hi>Goling</hi> and Colonell <hi>Newmarck</hi> were ſlaine. On our ſide amongſt the wounded is Colonell <hi>Shonbeck,</hi> Laſt night the French have taken Saint <hi>Iacobs</hi> Sconce, which lyes before the bridge of the City, inſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>much that we are now wholly maſters of the Rhine-bridge. Field-marſhall <hi>Goetz</hi> is retired to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards the black Forreſt. We doe not yet know what bootie we have obtained, only we ſee that the ſouldiers doe bring into their quarters many ſilken coats, and wagons loaden with muſquets and Pikes. At this preſent Field-marſhall <hi>Goetz</hi> ſtands again in <hi>Batalia.</hi> By all appearance he will venture once more, the effect whereof we ſhall ſee to morrow</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="71" facs="tcp:16041:36"/>
               <head>Another from the Campe the <hi>15. 25.</hi> of Oct.</head>
               <p>Yeſterday I doubt not but you have underſtood out of my Letter, the victory which God almigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie hath granted us. It is certaine that the enemy hath loſt above a thouſand men. This day Armes for two thouſand men have been taken up, which the Imperialliſts had throwne away. By all mens judgement Duke <hi>Bernhard</hi> by his owne ſtrength could not have bin able to beat the enemy againe out of the Sconces which they had taken; and therefore his Highneſſe and all the Colonells give the praiſe, next unto God, to the French, which fought like Lions, and gave quarter to none, but onely to ſeven or eight Captaines: Our high-Dutch have ſpared the lives of many Officers. Three chiefe Commanders whoſe names are not yet knowne, are ſlaine. Laſt night we thought the Enemy would have againe aſſaulted our Campe, but he departed ſuddenly in the night, and tooke his way toward Freybury, forſaking the other Sconce which he had yeſterday in his poſſeſſion. Our Horſemen are this day to follow him. Wee hope now to be ſhortly maſters of Briſſack. This day above eight hundred dead Souldiers have bin thrown into the River of Rhine, and in divers pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces many lie yet in the field unburied.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>
                  <hi>Strasburg</hi> the 19. 29. of <hi>Octob.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>The Imperiall Field-Marſhall <hi>Goetz</hi> for want of proviſion, is retiring with his Army towards Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fenburg.
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:16041:37"/> The report goes very ſtrong, that hee is to receive a ſuccour of 6000. men, which are ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken out of the Garriſons in Bavaria and other Countries, and is reſolved to trie his fortune once more. Beſides that, the D. of Savelle takes great paines to reforme the Duke of Lorraines Armie, and to relieve Briſſack on the ſame ſide. In the laſt aſſault are preſented unto Duke <hi>Bernhard</hi> 28 Captaines, together with Colonell <hi>Suyter,</hi> which are taken priſoners.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Paris the <hi>20. 30</hi> of October.</head>
               <p>From Italy is written, That both Armies are gone into Garriſon. The young Duke of Savoy is recovered againe of his ſickneſſe. The great Turke threatneth the Venetians with warre, yet the ſame Seigniory laboureth to compoſe the dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferences, and to appeaſe them with Preſents. The French Fleet in the Mediterranean Sea is gone towards Touton and Marſellies, to Winter there, and in the Ocean towards Rochell and Breſt. The Duke of Longueville with twelve hundred Horſe, and three thouſand Foot is gone towards Briſſack, and the Count of Arpenyan with two and twentie Companies of Horſe, and ſixe old Regiments of Foot, is gone towards Lor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raine, to joyne with Monſieur <hi>Belliford.</hi> The Prince of Lorraine brother to Duke <hi>Charles,</hi> lyes with two thouſand men about Vicy, and hath ſummoned Noyen. The ſuccour under the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:16041:37"/> of Monſieur <hi>Roquenſeniriere;</hi> conſiſting of two thouſand men, is ſpeedily marching towards Duke <hi>Bernhard</hi> of Weymar. Monſieur <hi>Haliere</hi> with his troops lye about Caſtilet, and Marſhall <hi>De la Foru</hi> about Guyſe, Prince <hi>Thomas</hi> and <hi>Pico<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lomini</hi> about Buvay; Monſieur <hi>Benedeſire</hi> hath preſented to His Majeſtie the King 21. Standards, which Duke <hi>Bernhard</hi> of Weymar hath taken from the Duke of Lorraine about Than.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Oſnabrug the <hi>27.</hi> of October, and the <hi>6.</hi> of November.</head>
               <p>In the Circle lyes two Swediſh Regiments, which ſtraggle continually abroad, and bring in daily many Imperiall Souldiers which they take priſoners. The diſperſed Palatine Cavallarie ſallieth againe about this Citie, and at Minden, and there are not ſo many miſſed as it was thought. The Palatine and Swediſh Officers which were taken Priſoners, in the laſt Battell are brought in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to Han, Munſter, Warendorp, and other places. Prince <hi>Robert,</hi> the Lieutenant Generall <hi>Ferentz,</hi> and two Engliſh Lords are at Warendorp. Prince <hi>Robert</hi> is within few dayes to be carried to Vienna. The Prince Elector Palatine himſelfe, Generall Major <hi>King,</hi> and the Officers are at Minden, onely Generall Major <hi>King</hi> is hurt in his ſhoulder, and one of his cheeks, but not dangerouſly. After the taken of Witlacken, the moſt part of the Hatz<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fieldiſh Horſemen arrived about Vecht, to beſiege
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:16041:38"/> the ſame place. Foure or five dayes agoe the Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie of Munſter hath ſent five Peeces of Ordnance to Generall <hi>Hatzfeld.</hi> Doubtleſſe he will uſe them in the ſiege. Duke <hi>George</hi> of Luneburg hath ſent certaine troops of horſe and foot from the River of Weſar towards Blekede. Colonell <hi>Slaugh</hi> with his commanded troops lyes yet at Lavenburg and Boytzenburg on the River of Elue, of which the Imperialiſts have ſurpriſed five hundred horſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men, and totally ruinated them.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Lower Saxony the <hi>29</hi> of October, and <hi>8.</hi> of November.</head>
               <p>The two and twentieth of October his Excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lencie Generall <hi>Bannier</hi> with his whole Army ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rived at Lawenburg, and hath arreſted all Ships, to lay a Ship-bridge over the River of Elve, and to make an invaſion into the Dukedome of Lune<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>burg. The Imperiall Generall <hi>Gallas</hi> with his Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my lyes about Rupin. Generall <hi>Klitſing</hi> about Berlin, and the Saxon troops about Wittenberg. The Palatine and Swediſh troopes under Gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall Major <hi>King,</hi> gather themſelves againe very ſtrong, and get great Succors. The peace with Heſſen (as is beleeved) will goe forward, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe the Emperour will ſuffer the reformed Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion in Heſſen. At this preſent the Citie of Vecht is ſtrongly beſieged by the Imperiall Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerall <hi>Hatzfeld,</hi> and from Munſter two Morter-Peeces are brought into the Campe. Thoſe of
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:16041:38"/> Oſnabrug have taken priſoner the Count <hi>Spar,</hi> who had about him eighteen thouſand Rixdollars in ready money, and certaine Standards, and was to command as Maſter of the Artillerle of the Hatzfeldiſh Army.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Luneburg the <hi>23.</hi> of October, and <hi>2.</hi> of Nomember.</head>
               <p>Yeſterday one thouſand horſe, and one thouſand foot, marched through this Citie, and ſome Regiments by it, they make up in all foure thouſand men belonging to Duke <hi>George</hi> of Brunſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wick, and Luneburg. They are brave and ſtout Souldiers, and are all going towards the River of Elve to oppoſe the Swedes which have threatned this Countrey. The Swedes maſter all ſtrong pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces in the Dukedome of Mecklenburg. They have lately taken Botzow, which lies three leagues from Guſtraw, and ſixe leagues from Roſtock; wherefore the ſame Duke will truſt them no far<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, but is gone with his Dutcheſſe to Brunſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wick.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Baſel the <hi>23.</hi> of October, and the <hi>2.</hi> of November.</head>
               <p>One part of the Duke of Lorraines troops had made a falſe alarum in one place of the Citie of Enſiſheim, into which part of the Lorraine foote Forces had retired, by that meanes to amaze the
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:16041:39"/> Weymariſh, which had given an aſſault upon the ſaid Towne, that in the meane time the ſaid Lor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raine foot Forces might ſave themſelves by flight: But Colonell <hi>Roſa</hi> perceiving their plot, prevented them immediatly with his troops, and lay in wait for them about Cwittelsback, neere a wood where hee fell upon them, totally routed and defeated them, ſlew many, and tooke priſoners two hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred horſe, and foure hundred foot alſo. Which willingly take ſervice under Duke <hi>Bernhard</hi> of Weymar, Generall Major <hi>Mercy,</hi> with no more but thirty horſe-men fled to Than. Colonell <hi>Cuelyers</hi> Lieutenant Colonell, and two and twenty other Lorraine Officers are taken priſoners. Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lonell <hi>Roſa</hi> purſued the reſt into the wood. The Imperiall Field-Marſhall <hi>Goetz,</hi> with his Army did the like, and made a ſhew as if hee would goe to this ſide of the Rhine towards Colmar: but now wee heare that hee is ſeeking already his winter Quarters in the countrey of Wirtenburg towards Tubingen. It ſeemeth that he hath no great mind more to aſſault our Sconces: We hope now that Briſſack, in which the beſieged are in great di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtreſſe, by the helpe of God will ſhortly be ſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rendred.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Alſatia the <hi>26.</hi> of October, the <hi>5.</hi> of November.</head>
               <p>It is certaine that the Duke of Lorraine <hi>de No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vo</hi> is routed and defeated neere Enſiſheim by the Weymariſh Colonell <hi>Roſa,</hi> who commanded
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:16041:39"/> one thouſand horſe, and two thouſand foot, the moſt part of the Lorrainers have taken ſervice un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der Duke <hi>Bernhard;</hi> the report goes, of neere upon one hundred Officers that were taken priſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners. Laſt Friday Duke <hi>Bernhard</hi> of Weymar cauſed the Citie of Briſſack to bee ſummoned by a Trumpeter, the Governour <hi>Reinacher</hi> beſtowed a quart of Rhiniſh wine upon the Trumpetter, and ſent him word, that hee as an honeſt Souldier ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pected the promiſed reliefe, and ſixe dayes hence hee ſhould come againe.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>S<hi rend="sup">t</hi>. Germaine the <hi>27.</hi> of October, the <hi>6.</hi> of November.</head>
               <p>The Armies in Italie lie yet on both ſide in Garriſon, the Spanlſh Forces lie partly in the Dukedome of Millaine, and partly in Montferat: the French Foot-forces lie likewiſe in ſome part of Montferat, and the Horſe-men in Del<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phinate. His Majeſtie the King hath ſent for di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers Colonells, which have beene this yeare in the field, to come to the Court; ſome are beleeved will not fare well.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Bremen the <hi>1. 11.</hi> of Novemb.</head>
               <p>The Prince Elector Palatine, together with Generall Major <hi>King,</hi> is yet at Minden, and drawes together his Troopes from all places. Heere are paſſed by this Citie ſeven hundred
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:16041:40"/> new levyed ſouldiers for the ſayd Prince Ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctor, all foot, which are marching towards their Randevouz; fifteene hundred more are daily to follow them with certaine peeces of Ordnance, a certaine ſumme of Money, and great ſtore of Ammunition.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Hamborough the <hi>3. 13.</hi> of Novemb.</head>
               <p>His Excellency Generall <hi>Bannier</hi> hath his Head quarter a league from Swerin, being eight leagues from the River of Elve. The Imperiall Generall <hi>Gallas</hi> lyes at Grabau; both Armies approach one to another, inſomuch that many beleeve, that within few dayes it will come to a pitch'd battell. Generall <hi>Hatzfeld</hi> hath order to joyne with the aforeſayd Generall <hi>Gallas;</hi> to which end a Bridge is to bee layd over the River of Elve at Domitz. The Inhabitants of the Dukedome of Mecklen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>burg write of great miſery, which they endure in the ſayd Countrey.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Franckford the <hi>11. 21.</hi> of Novemb.</head>
               <p>As for Newes we have none other at this time, but that the ſame which I wrote unto you laſt weeke is confirmed, namely, that <hi>Duc de Savelly</hi> is totally routed. At this inſtant wee receive A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſoes from Vlin, that Bryſſack is ſurrendred. The like they write from Lyon, Paris, and other places.</p>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="81" facs="tcp:16041:40"/>
            <head>An Abstract of the <hi>NOREMBERG</hi> Curranto.</head>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Baſill the <hi>25</hi> of October, <hi>5</hi> of Novemb.</head>
               <p>WHen yeſterday was ſeven-night, Duke <hi>Bernehard</hi> of <hi>Wymar</hi> went to Prayers: a great Eagle flew about the <hi>Weymariſh</hi> Campe, and about Duke <hi>Bernehards</hi> Tent; as if he would ſit upon it; afterwards he flew againe into the Mountaines, which was ſeene by all thoſe that were in the Campe.</p>
               <p>After that the <hi>Lorraine</hi> troopes had taken the City of <hi>Enſiſheim,</hi> and guarded it with 500 men, the Sweediſh garriſon that lay in it, retired into the Caſtle, from whence they ſhot fiercely into the City, whereupon the <hi>Lorraine</hi> Generall Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jor <hi>Mercy</hi> (of whoſe troopes, 400 Horſe had likewiſe taken the little City of <hi>Munſter,</hi> in St. <hi>Georges</hi> vallie, and obtained Colonell <hi>Callenbuchs</hi> Baggage, and afterward fired the ſaid City) with 500 horſe, and 500 Foot, together with two pieces of Ordinances, went likewiſe to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:16041:41"/> 
                  <hi>Enſiſheim</hi> to maſter the Caſtle, wherefore Duke <hi>Bernehard</hi> of <hi>Weymar,</hi> commanded thither<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards Colonell <hi>Roſa</hi> with five regiments of horſe to keepe the ſame place block'd up, till the fifteene hundred commanded Muſquetiers, and ſix pieces of Ordinances, did follow him to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve the Caſtle, but Generall Major <hi>Mercy,</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing loath to expect him, betooke himſelfe with his troopes, together with the garriſon out of <hi>Enſiſheim,</hi> and thought to eſcape through the wood, neare <hi>Wildeſhim,</hi> but Colonell <hi>Roſa</hi> lay in wait for him there, aſſaulted him, and totally rou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted and diſperſed his troopes, that Generall Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jor <hi>Mercy,</hi> onely with thirty horſemen fled into <hi>Than,</hi> foure hundred Foot, and two hundred Horſe of his troopes, together with their Offi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cers, tooke willingly ſervice under the <hi>Weyma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſh,</hi> the reſt were knocked downe in the wood, and Colonell <hi>Roſa</hi> hath taken priſoner Generall Maior <hi>Mercy's</hi> Lieutenant, Colonell, and twen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty two other Officers, and obtained two pieces of Ordnances, inſomuch that now the whole <hi>Lor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raine</hi> Armie is ruinated.</p>
               <p>The Prince Elector <hi>Palatine,</hi> and the Swediſh Generall King, recollect their forces, as much as they can, and are reſolved to ſeeke their revenge.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Leipzig, the <hi>2. 12.</hi> of Novemb.</head>
               <p>The Diet of the Circle of upper <hi>Saxonie,</hi> takes
<gap reason="illegible: missing" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="83" facs="tcp:16041:41"/> here is beginning, to which end, yeſterday are ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rived here Imperiall Electorall, and Princely Deputies, as alſo other Peeres of the circle of up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per <hi>Saxonie,</hi> and thereupon yeſterday, and this day in the forenoone, they have met together in the Towne-hall: what they will conclude, time will ſhew.</p>
               <p>Both Armies in <hi>Pomerania,</hi> lay now ſtill, on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Generall <hi>Gallas,</hi> cauſeth the ſhip-bridge to bee laid againe over the <hi>Elve</hi> at <hi>Domitz,</hi> and all the proviſion that lyes at <hi>Maideburg, Tangermund,</hi> as alſo at <hi>Hamberough</hi> is carryed thither, it ſeemeth that they intend to march againe into the Duke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome of <hi>Mecklenburg,</hi> and we heare that <hi>Bannier</hi> is already marched towards <hi>Wiſmar.</hi> The City of <hi>VVitſtocke</hi> is fired in divers places, &amp; burn'd down to the ground.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>From the Campe before Bryſſack, the <hi>25.</hi> of Octob. the <hi>5.</hi> of Nov.</head>
               <p>Certaine dayes agoe, Duke <hi>Bernhard</hi> of <hi>Wey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mar,</hi> ſummoned <hi>Bryſſack,</hi> unto whom the Gover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour made a gracious anſwer: Duke <hi>Bernhard</hi> hath intercepted Letters, being dated the 9. 19 of of <hi>October,</hi> in which the Governour <hi>Reinacher</hi> writes, that he hath no more but for two dayes bread, and for ſome few dayes yet fleſh, and that the moſt part of his ſouldiers, yea above the halfe part, eſpecially the Officers are ſicke, dead, runne
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:16041:42"/> away, &amp; diſcontented, and that they have ſet him time, from the 26 of <hi>Aug.</hi> 6 weekes to relieve him, which were expired above halfe, if ſo bee it did not goe well, he would be blameleſſe, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe all things were now brought to extreame, what troubled him moſt, he durſt not write, and that he diſſembled ſo much, that he hopes that the enemy will not perceive it, and that notwithſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſting he will doe his beſt indeavour, and yeeld in nothing to the <hi>Hermerſteiners, &amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>From the Campe before Bryſſack, the <hi>30.</hi> of Octob. the <hi>10.</hi> of Nov.</head>
               <p>Yeſterday the beſieged did forſake their mill Sconce, againſt which we have approached theſe 2 dayes together, the mill they have fired in ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verall places: the night thereupon following, Duke <hi>Bernhard</hi> of <hi>Weymar,</hi> commanded <hi>Viſcount de Turenne, &amp; Monſier de Rogue,</hi> ſervices againſt a Hill, called <hi>Eyſenberg,</hi> which they tooke by aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſault, and tooke priſoners, one Captaine, and 30 ſouldiers, of the <hi>Wymariſh</hi> ſouldiers were but 2. hurt, inſomuch that the beſieged have now no out-workes more: yeſterday Duke <hi>Bernehard</hi> hath ſent againe a Trumpeter into the City, and hath offered to the Governour <hi>Reinacher</hi> very honou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable conditions, and withall warned him, that if ſo be he did ſtand out longer againſt all reaſons and conſcience, He would not take it ill, if his highneſſe here fter did not deale with them, as an honeſt Cavallier.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="85" facs="tcp:16041:42"/>
               <head>An Extract of a Letter from <hi>Imlingon,</hi> the <hi>30.</hi> of October <hi>10.</hi> of November.</head>
               <p>After that the French Army under the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand of Monſieur <hi>de Feuguieres,</hi> had blocked up the City of <hi>Luneville,</hi> and received intelli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gence, that the Duke of <hi>Savelly</hi> with his Army, was in the way to march by <hi>Imlingen,</hi> &amp; to joyn with the Duke of <hi>Lorraine,</hi> the ſaid Monſieur <hi>de Feuguieres,</hi> immediatly broke up from before <hi>Luneville,</hi> and the 26. of October, about eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, with 16. or 1700. horſe, tooke his quar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter in the foreſaid Towne of <hi>Imlingen,</hi> where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the Duke of <hi>Saville</hi> having received intelli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gence of it, marched towards <hi>Blamount,</hi> where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon Monſieur <hi>de Feuguieres</hi> in the evening, an houre before night, broke up againe and tooke his quarter in the village of <hi>Singrichen,</hi> the next day after being the 28. day of October, hee quartered betwixt <hi>Airecourt</hi> and <hi>Blaumont,</hi> into which, (namely <hi>Blaumont</hi>) all the <hi>Savelliſh</hi> foote forces together with certaine troopes of horſe, and all their Baggage came, where Monſieur <hi>de Feugieres,</hi> immediately routed and defeated all the foot, and made them yeeld upon diſcre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and obtained all their Wagons, that were loaden with the Baggage and ammunition, about 88. together with three barrels with mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny, and immediately thereupon ſurrounded the little City and Caſtle of <hi>Blanckenburg,</hi> in which the Duke of <hi>Saville</hi> with all reſt of horſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:16041:43"/> layes, inſomuch that no man can get in or out: In the meane time the Duke of <hi>Longuevil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>le,</hi> with certaine 1000. men, hath likewiſe joy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned with Monſieur <hi>de Feugieres,</hi> inſomuch that the Duke of <hi>Saville</hi> together with all thoſe that are about him, are in a trap, becauſe they have not to looke for any ſuccour or relieve; much leſſe have they any proviſion, either for men or horſe: and beſides the ſaid place is not ſtrong at all. At this inſtant wee receive aviſoes, that the ſaid Duke of <hi>Savelly</hi> with 30. horſe men, by a ſtratageme hath got out of the Towne, and ſaved himſelfe by flight very narrowly.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>From the Biſhoprike of <hi>Bremen</hi> the <hi>10. 20.</hi> of November.</head>
               <p>Certaine dayes agoe arrived at <hi>Veyhſack</hi> in this Biſhoprick 700. Souldiers both <hi>Engliſh Scots,</hi> and other nations, taken up by Colonell <hi>Vale<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kener,</hi> for the Prince Electour <hi>Palatine,</hi> which thought to march through the City of <hi>Bremen,</hi> but the Magiſtrate of the ſaid City, refuſed and granted them onely paſſage below the Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty over the River of <hi>Weſar.</hi> Our Biſhop having received intelligence of it, ſummon'd with all ſpeed all his ſubjects, and ſtrictly charged every one to let no man paſſe, which they did accordingly, and drove the ſaid <hi>Palatine</hi> troops, to the very gates of the City of <hi>Bremen,</hi> where they lay two days together without victuals, atlaſt they were faine to run away, and to ſhift for themſelves as well as they could.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="87" facs="tcp:16041:43"/>
               <head>Minden the <hi>11. 21.</hi> November.</head>
               <p>The Prince Elector <hi>Palatine</hi> is yet here, and by all appearance will continue here this Win<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter. Lieutenant Generall <hi>King,</hi> hath recolle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted his troopes, both of horſe and foo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ut firſt of all they will be laid into garriſon to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>freſh themſelves with order to leave no reſt to the enemy in all wherof Colonell <hi>Coningsmarck,</hi> hath done already a proove, aſſaulted and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feated the Imperiall Reereguard, and taken di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſe Officers and common Souldiers, priſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners: together with certaine ſtandards. Hee hath brought hither into the City. Other par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties are at this preſent likewiſe in the field, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſomuch that the priſons are made full, and the Imperialiſts, will not be able to lay long be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twixt our garriſons.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>From the Biſhoprike of <hi>Munſter</hi> the <hi>11. 21.</hi> November.</head>
               <p>The Imperialiſts have forſaken the ſiege be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore <hi>Witluken,</hi> the Imperiall Generall <hi>Hatzfeld,</hi> hath taken <hi>Cloppenburgh,</hi> and batters now fierce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly the City of <hi>Vecht,</hi> but by reaſon of the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinuall raine, he cannot approach, becauſe the ſaid place is by nature moriſh and waterie, his Souldiers ſtood in the approaches above the knees in the water.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Colen <hi>the</hi> 11. 21. <hi>of November.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>We have received certaine Aviſoes, that the Imperiall Fieldmarſhall <hi>Goetz,</hi> is ſtrictly change d by the Emperour to relieve <hi>Bryſiack,</hi>
                  <pb n="88" facs="tcp:16041:44"/> although hee ſhould conſume and ruinate the whole Army; others write, that hee is to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pect, firſt the comming of <hi>Piccolomeni,</hi> whoſe troopes are marching towards the River of <hi>Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſell:</hi> He himſelfe in perſon was with the laſt letters, yet at <hi>Bruſsells.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Vleſsing the <hi>17. 27</hi> of Nov.</head>
               <p>From hence are gone to Sea, diverſe ſhips, towards England and <hi>France,</hi> they have along with them, for a convey, 3 men of Warre, as namely <hi>Bastian Thys</hi> of the <hi>Veere, Abraham Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>runis,</hi> and Captaine <hi>Holuert:</hi> the ſaid <hi>Holuert,</hi> and <hi>Corunis,</hi> are to croſſe the Sea, when they have brought their ſhips into ſafety: In the ſame Fleet, went a Prince of <hi>Polen,</hi> and the Sonne of Marſhall <hi>de Chatillion.</hi> A partie of our ſouldi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers in the Sconce of <hi>Philippina,</hi> have beene a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>broad, whereof ſome did ſwimme over the Ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver of <hi>Ley,</hi> amongſt which was one, who could well play his part with lamenting &amp; groaning that he got a Prieſt out of his houſe, in a cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine village, to make his confeſſion to his Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, as he cal'd him, becauſe he was a dying: And although the Prieſt did not doe it willing<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, becauſe it was night, yet notwithſtanding, out of compaſſion, as alſo by interceſſion of the Maid, was moved to goe along, and when they had him without his dore, they made him keep ſilence by threatnings, and tied a towell about him, and hailed him along with them over the River, and thus brought him into <hi>Philippina</hi> Sconce. He is a very rich Prieſt.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="89" facs="tcp:16041:44"/>
               <head>Vienna the <hi>30</hi> of October the <hi>10</hi> of November.</head>
               <p>THis weeke his Imperiall Majeſty hath beene a Hunting and kill'd above 100 wild Boares, and in the hunting hath eſcaped a great miſchance, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe the great wind tore out a great tree with the rootes, which fell downe cloſe by his Imperiall Majeſtie yet without any hurt to him.</p>
               <p>At Prague the ſickneſſe begins to be very briefe, many Spirituall and Laymen betake themſelves into the Country: About the ſaid City are likewiſe growne ſtrange wormes, which have almoſt ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten up all the ſowne corne.</p>
               <p>From Hungary wee are certified, that the Tur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kiſh Army before Babilon about 300000 ſtrong is totally routed and defeated, inſomuch that the Turkiſh Emperour ſaved himſelfe onely with few men, who hath charged now all the Baſſas in Hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>garie to give no cauſe or occaſion to the Chriſtians to warres.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Baſil <hi>2. 12.</hi> of November.</head>
               <p>FRom the Campe before Briſack we are certi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied, that the 29. of October, many skaling ladders have beene brought into the Campe, and the ſame day the beſieged for want of Souldiers have forſaken the Awemill, fired it, and carryed the Canons into the towne, which Mil is now guar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded
<pb n="90" facs="tcp:16041:45"/> by the Weymariſh, the night thereupo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the French have taken the Moas hill, and obtai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned upon it 5 peeces of Ordnances, inſomuch that they have now in their poſſeſſion all the out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>works of the City on both ſides; whereupon Duke <hi>Bernhard</hi> ſent a Trumpeter into the City, who is not yet returned back againe, Fieldmarſhall <hi>Goetz</hi> lyes yet in the Blackwood: The French ſuccour conſiſting of 4000. foote and 1500. horſe is Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching towards Dudel upon their arrivall, it is thought Duke <hi>Bernhard</hi> will give an aſſault upon the City of Briſack, the Souldiers, which come daily out of the City unto us, certifie, that many men are already dead and ſtarved for want of food, the moſt part of the Souldiers lye ſick: The Duke of Longoville hath received order from the King of France, to go into Lorraine and to recover a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine Eſpinael and other places: The ſecond of this moneth the Auſtrian Citie of Bludentz happened on fire, and within the ſpace of 4 houres was bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned downe to the ground.</p>
               <p>Colonell <hi>Flenheim</hi> 3. daies a go upo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> order of Duke <hi>Bernhard</hi> of Weymar is gone againſt the Boores, what he will effect, we ſhall ſhortly heare. The con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>federate Switzers are yet together at Baden treating about the Neutrality of Burgundy.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Freyburg the <hi>5</hi> or <hi>15</hi> of November,</head>
               <p>THe City of Briſack lies now a bleeding be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the Gutenburg, Fieldmarſhall <hi>Goetz</hi> hath
<pb n="91" facs="tcp:16041:45"/> loſt 3 aſſaults, the ſaid City is but little, yet ſtrong and with few Souldiers guarded. Generall Major <hi>Lamboy</hi> with 800 men, is gone upon another ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ploit. Duk <hi>Bernhard</hi> of Weymar hath ſent the Cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taines, which hee hath taken upon the Ecken-hill, without any ranſon into Briſack, to certifie the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernour of that which they have ſeene, eſpecially of the overthrowes of the Duke of Lorraine and the Duke of Savelly, which overthrowes the beſieged will not beleeve: The runne awaies, that came laſt out of Briſack declare all vnanimouſly, that the ſaid City is in great diſtreſſe, all the Cats and Dogs in it are eaten up, a pound of Horſe fleſh is ſold for 12 pence, every third day each Souldier received as much bread as the bigneſſe of an apple, and that not above 200 fighting men now are in the City.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Venice the <hi>2. 12</hi> of November.</head>
               <p>The 19. 29 of October, the Governour of Caſſal <hi>Octavio de Montegli</hi> was beheaded. Hee is accuſed by the French that he intended to ſurrender the ſaid Caſtle unto the Spaniards.</p>
               <p>From Conſtantinople is comfirmed the over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>throw of the Turkiſh Army before Babilonia, wher 50000. Turkes were ſlaine, wherefore at Conſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinople the ſhips and goods, not onely of the Vene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tians, but alſo of all other Chriſtians, are ſet at li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Erfurd the <hi>10. 20</hi> of November.</head>
               <p>The Emperiall Generall <hi>Gallas</hi> with his Army lyes yet about Waldesleben, the ſhipbridge is <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>aid about Lentz over the River of Elve, the Lunebur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſh troopes about 4000 ſtrong, and Generall <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rozini</hi>
                  <pb n="92" facs="tcp:16041:46"/> with 5000 men of the Saxon troops are like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe marching to the Gallaſſiſh Army, which can be victualled for a time from Domitz, and within few dayes they are to goe over the River of Elve, againſt Generall <hi>Bannier,</hi> who hath great want of Horſes, and had ſome loſſe before Damine.</p>
               <p>The Imperiall propoſition is made at Leipzig, the circle of upper and lower Saxonie ſhall maintaine 18000, foote, and 8000. horſe, and beſides the maintenance and ſervice of the reformed Regi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, pay 1932370. Florens, th'tother circles are not taxed ſo high, and the Imperiall hereditarie Countries are kept exempt and free, inſomuch that this meeting will produce ſtrange things, the States and Peeres inſtead of paying pretend their poverty and diſtruction of their Countries, together with many diſpleaſures and burdens.</p>
               <p>The Swediſh &amp; Palatine troops that lay at Minden &amp; Oſnabrug ſtraggle very ſtrong up and downe, and have take<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> priſoner Colonel <hi>Otto, Chriſtopher</hi> of Spar who ſhould have beene Generall Sergeant Major of the Hatzfeldiſh Army, and tooke from him 14. Standards &amp; Enſignes, which the Imperialliſts had taken from the Swedes in Gartz and Wolgaſt.</p>
               <p>The D. of Savelly is defeated again by the French upon the frontiers of Burgundy, &amp; himſelf eſcaped only with 30 Horſemen: Generall Major <hi>Lamboy</hi> with his troopes is arrived againe about Darmſtat, why he hath ſeperated himſelf from Fieldmarſhall <hi>Goetz</hi> is not knowne.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="93" facs="tcp:16041:46"/>
               <head>Spandaw the <hi>7</hi> or <hi>17</hi> of November.</head>
               <p>THe Swediſh Generall <hi>Bannier</hi> lies yet about Swerin, certaine troupes of his ſouldiers have beſieged the Warmunder Sconce neere Roſtock. The Imperiall Generall <hi>Gallas</hi> with his army lyes yet about Lentz and Waldeſlechen.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Leipzig the <hi>10</hi> or <hi>20</hi> of November.</head>
               <p>The Dyet here continues yet. From Pruſſia is certified, that the Elector of Brandenburg going a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>broad in his coach, a ſhot was made downe from a houſe, which went through the coach and the brim of his hat, without doing him any hurt.</p>
               <p>At this inſtant we receive aviſoes, that the Impe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riall field Marſhall <hi>Goetz</hi> preſenteth himſelfe in the valley about Oldkerck in full battell array.</p>
               <p>An Expreſſe which this day came hither brings news, that the ſaid field Marſhal <hi>Goetz</hi> with certain 1000 men hath fallen againe upon Colonel <hi>Morſers</hi> Sconce and Quarter before Briſack, but after that he had made three aſſaults upon it, hee was beaten off and forced to retyre with the loſſe of 2000 men.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Paris the <hi>10</hi> or <hi>20</hi> of November.</head>
               <p>DVke de la Valette is fled with 50000 piſtolets into England; wherefore Duke d' Eſpernon
<pb n="94" facs="tcp:16041:47"/> is more narrowly looked to at Blaſack. The report goes that the Cardinal de la Vallette goes to Rome and Duke de Candale to Venice. Monſieur de Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry is called backe againe and arrived at Grenoble: in a word, many alterations fall in the Court about the Offices.</p>
               <p>The Griſons can get no audience neither with the Archdutcheſſe of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>yrol, nor with the Marques de Leganes, which by all appearance wil cauſe new troubles.</p>
               <p>Laſt Sunday came hither a Page from duke <hi>Bernard</hi> of Weymar, who ſolliciteth for aſſiſtance. In al the Provinces great forces and monies are gathered to continue the war next ſpring with all ſeveritie.</p>
               <p>This day arrived here an Expreſſe, who came from the Duke of Longeville, relating that the duke of Savellies troups are totally routed and defeated. beſides 500 horſmen more which lay in Blaumont, and yeelded upon diſcretion, with all the baggage and Chancery of the ſaid duke of Savelly.</p>
               <p>Monſieur <hi>Preul</hi> hath likewiſe defeated about Dourlans 500 horſemen.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Hamborough the <hi>14</hi> or <hi>24</hi> of November.</head>
               <p>HIs Excellencie Generall <hi>Bannier</hi> hath his head quarter yet at New Cloyſter, where hee doth re-inforce himſelfe, and hath cauſed above 3000 horſes to be brought, becauſe many of his horſes died, and neere upon 5000 horſemen went a foot.
<pb n="95" facs="tcp:16041:47"/> His Majeſty the King of France hath <hi>de novo</hi> made over by bills of Exchange to Generall <hi>Bannier</hi> a great ſum of mony:</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Bremen the <hi>16</hi> or <hi>26</hi> of November.</head>
               <p>The city of Vecht, in which the Swediſh garri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon defended it ſelfe ſtoutly, was ſurrendred the 14 or 24 day of this moneth by compoſition, unto the Imperiall Generall <hi>Hatzfield,</hi> and the Swediſh gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſon was conducted towards Minden. D<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>vers Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>periall high officers have beene ſlaine in this ſiege, as namely Generall Serjeant Major <hi>Weſterholt,</hi> a young Count of Pappenheim, and above 300 com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon ſouldiers. At this inſtant we receive likewiſe Aviſoes, that an Imperial convoy with ammunition going from hence towards the Imperiall camp, was aſſaulted about Wilſhouſen by 80 Swediſh horſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men that came out of Nienburg, and totally routed and defeated, and all the gun-pouder blowne up.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Maſtricht the <hi>17</hi> or <hi>27</hi> of November.</head>
               <p>LAſt Monday the French horſemen went a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>broad from hence, and have pillaged in the country of Gulick, Geelkercken and other places, and are returned hither againe with a rich booty. At this inſtant by beating of the drumme is publiſhed, that all merchants in the Biſhopricke of Collen, country of Gulick, and Haken, may free and with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out
<pb n="96" facs="tcp:16041:48" rendition="simple:additions"/> hindrance come hither into this city with their wares, and that they ſhall not bec moleſted or trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled by the Frenh.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Collen the <hi>17</hi> or <hi>27</hi> of November.</head>
               <p>WIth the laſt letters from Strausburg is writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten, that duke <hi>Bernard</hi> of Weymar hath ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken the Eckenberger ſconce, and being he under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtood by the priſoners the great diſtreſſe of the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſieged, hee was reſolved to aſſault them by force.</p>
               <p>The Imperiall General Sergeant Major <hi>Horſt</hi> with 3000 horſemen is gone toward Stollhoven to paſſe the river of Rhine. Wee heare of no great ſuccour ſent unto Field Marſhall <hi>Goetz,</hi> inſomuch that the relieving of Briſack is much doubted.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Amſterdam the <hi>25</hi> of Nov. or <hi>4</hi> of December.</head>
               <p>This weeke are arrived in the Ulie between two and 300 ſhips, which came from the Eaſt Countries and Norway.</p>
               <p>The Weſt India Company in theſe provinces continues yet ſtrongly with their preparations, and above 1600 brave ſoldiers are already muſtred and ſhipped, and 3000 more are to be taken up.</p>
               <p>From Barcellona are ſent towards Italy 370 cheſts with Ryals of eight, for the continuing of the war in Italy.</p>
               <pb facs="tcp:16041:48"/>
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
